Okay. Um, good morning. Um,
welcome back.
So, there are a couple of outstanding
issues from last class that I would like
to uh address. So, Carol's son uh who
was here, he had a question about what
is difference between pride and ego.
And this is a very hard question. Okay.
So first let's think about think about
what the ego is. So in the cabala
tradition
uh and the cabala tradition is very much
um influenced by the divine comedy. If
you learn the cabala and you read the
divine comedy you see a lot of
similarities and these are not
coincidental but in the cabala tradition
um there is divine spark in everyone but
it's covered by the husk. Okay, the husk
you can say it's the body, it's the ego,
but the but for the Gabala tradition the
ego is basically just the body and the
desire to fulfill the body which means
material pleasures. Okay, so in the
Cabala tradition that's what the ego
means. Dante doesn't see it that way. Um
for Dante the ego is really the divine
spark.
Okay? In that it can propel us to uh
good things and to bad things. So it's
potentiality as opposed to just good or
bad. Okay? It's it's potential
potentiality. Uh and the ego can lead us
astray. And when it leads us to astray,
it's because of pride. Okay? And so for
Dante, pride is an issue because it
wants you. It wants
um the other egos to subordinate to your
ego. All right? So, it's one of
superiority, a feeling of superiority
where you are above others.
And for Donnie, that's a problem because
that limits your access to God. Okay?
Love is about equality. It's about uh
being egotarian and treating others with
respect and trusting others. And the
ego, the pride, it's about
um
elevating yourself above others. Okay.
And the classic example of pride in the
mind comedy is Virgil, right? Virgil.
[snorts]
Okay. So that's the difference for um in
most religious traditions there's really
they don't really separate the two. Ego
is pride but for Dante there is a
difference. Ego is potentiality. It's
possibility and pride is a perversion of
the ego. Okay. The ego should lead
should lead you towards faith, hope and
love. And without the ego you could not
actually go on this path.
But um if you go on the wrong path, it
leads you to pride. Okay. And again uh
in the in the divine comedy even though
it is not explicit uh Virgil is the
manifestation the expression of pride.
Okay. And we can see that in his actions
um where
um he uh but it'll become more obvious
as as we go as we go along. Okay. So
that's the first issue. Does does it
make sense to everyone? Okay. Uh second
issue is the issue of homosexuality.
Okay.
And this is an issue
that raised concerns
um so one question that I was asked
yesterday is okay
um what's the difference between
homosexuality and heterosexuality? Okay.
So so it so so thank you for for
phrasing that that question. And I went
back and I thought about this and even
though my explanation it's okay, it's
not truthful enough because the way for
us to understand truth is AAM's razor.
Okay, Aam's razor is the idea of
elegance. Meaning I should be very I
should be able to pretty simply and
clearly explain the idea and I and I was
not able to do that yesterday. It raised
a lot of questions. It raised a lot of
doubts. So even though we were
approaching the truth, we were not at
the truth. So let me today try to
more clearly and simply explain the
problem of of of homosexuality. Okay?
And so um
yesterday I made things a bit
complicated. I brought in the idea of
incest and that was very confusing.
Okay? Let's not do that. Okay? Let's
just like stick with Dante. So with
Dante, the key to understanding him is
to first appreciate the punishment at
work. Okay? Because for Dante, the
punishment is God's perfect justice.
Okay? So we need to understand the
punishment first. And the punishment for
these homosexuals is they are in a
plains where like there's raining
missiles on them. Okay? And so they have
to dodge these missiles. For
homosexuals, they have to do it in a
group.
Okay, they have to do it in a group and
if one of them strays from the group,
that person is punished harder.
Now, this is interesting to think about
because
why would homosexuals be punished in
such a manner? Okay, so now we we think
about let's not think about what they
did wrong, but if the punishment is you
have to stick together as a group and
you're being punished as a group and if
you fall away from the group, you're
punished even harder. What kind of
people
should be punished like that?
Right? If we knew what the punishment is
and we understand that these punishments
are reflection of God's perfect justice,
then what kind of people, what did you
do wrong in society that would make God
punish you like this?
Uh yes.
>> Uh they think they think they're like
superior to the to the society as a
general. Like they're they feel like
they're entitled. So they're they feel
like they're above like uh like the
normal people.
>> Good. Okay. So that's getting somewhere.
Okay. But again, what do they do wrong?
That sounds like pride, but why are they
being punished as a group?
Yes,
>> you know maybe uh homosexual things is
kind of group just for male or for
female. So if in that case the male they
don't need a female and female also
don't need a male too. So maybe they're
enemy of each other.
>> Right. Right. Let's not think about like
their homosexual. I'm saying what kind
of people would deserve the sort of
punishment.
>> Yes.
Um, in that conception, people who are
super self-centered, you want to force
them to be in a group and think as a
group.
>> Okay, that makes sense. Okay. Yeah.
People who are too selfish and so they
have to work together, but they're not
they're not working together. They're
being punished together, right?
So basically, it's idea of factionalism,
right? or mafia
or fraternity.
Does that make sense? Because the idea
of fraternity, the idea of mafia, the
idea of factionalism is that you only
care about your own group and you're
going to hurt others in order to achieve
your own interests. And that's why
they're being punished like this. Okay?
So now if if it's these people who are
engaged in mafia or fraternity or
factionalism that are should be p that
that would be punished like this. What
does this have to do with homosexuality?
Okay, that's a question. All right, and
again this should be clear. All right,
so so make sure that my logic is clear
to you each step of the way. Right, the
punishment is they're being punished for
factionalism. The question then is what
does this have to do with homosexuality?
Okay. Yes.
>> No. Coming back. So like say in the
mafia you act in some way and then
you're part of the mafia forever. And we
could see the same pattern in
homosexuality.
>> Right. Have Have you guys heard
something called the gay mafia?
Pig mafia. Gay mafia.
Okay. These are people people who
control Hollywood. Right. If you go to
Hollywood, they're like we're controlled
by the pig mafia. the gay mafia. All
right. So, so, so, so, so let let me
explain this. Okay. All right. So, ideal
society,
everyone should rise according to his or
her individual merit. Right? In an ideal
society, that's what Donnie believes.
Like, it doesn't matter what faction you
are. It doesn't matter where your family
comes from. It doesn't matter. All that
matters is your individual merit. That
that's what's ideal.
But in reality, the people who often
triumph are people who are able to
conspire together.
Right? So
the question then is
how are homosexuals able to conspire
together? Okay. So, and the reason why
is they're often persecuted by society.
So, they have to work in secret.
Okay. And so they help each other in
order to obtain success. They're not not
doing it out of evil or malice. They're
doing it just to like be able to love
each other. Okay? And so that's why if
you just look at history, if you look at
any bureaucracy in any society, the
group of people who often climb [snorts]
highest in this bureaucracy tend to be
homosexuals. Doesn't make sense. Okay.
And you go back to Imperial China,
the Unix, right? You sorry, you go to
the Vatican, right? You go to Washington
DC, you go to Hollywood.
It's usually homosexuals that climb to
the top. Again, this is not being I'm
not saying this is evil, but like just
so that they can practice your love for
each other. They have to work together,
okay?
and they have to help each other and so
they become a mafia, right? The pig
mafia, the gay mafia and but because of
mafia they're able to climb higher
together because they're able to
coordinate together secretly in a way
that others are not able to. Does that
make sense? Uh yes.
>> Could this be linked to your like
previous ideas that like by breaking
taboo like uh bond is generated?
>> Yes. Yes. Okay. Uh yes. And that also
explains why if one breaks away then
he's punished harder because he's
breaking the vow to the group and the
secret that he had to
>> Exactly. Exactly. Right. Exactly. Thank
you very much. And the other issue is
okay like why can't heterosexuals do
this? Because if you're a het
heterosexual you marry a woman, right?
And the woman demand demands that only
you are loyal to her. Whereas with gay
lovers, you can share with others,
right? You can expand the group in a way
you can't expand the group if you were
heterosexual. Does it make sense? All
right. Okay. Are you guys following this
logic?
Okay. Now, now the question then is like
why would this be a bad thing? A bad and
the reason why is that if a certain
group are able to amass more power for
themselves, right? This forces other
people to form their own factions. Does
it make sense? in order to compete. You
have no choice in the matter,
right? So now you have more factionalism
going on.
All right? And so now what happens is
that the elite fight amongst themselves
because it's factional politics now. And
when the elite fights fight amongst
themselves, they're able what they're
doing is they're monopolizing all
resources for themselves, which creates
more inequality, right, in society. If
you if you don't have a faction, when
most people don't have a faction, you're
completely screwed.
And so there's this massive inequality
which creates all this economic
pressure. And the only way for you to
respond if you're an ordinary person, a
faction is to commit fraud, right? And
then what happens is lawlessness takes
place.
So um that's why DA is concerned about
homosexuality. He knows that yes, these
best and brightest are are homosexuals
and he and for him there's nothing wrong
with homosexuality. It's what
homosexuality leads to in the society
that's a problem. And Donnie is right.
If you just look at any society, okay,
with a bureaucracy, eventually the
homosexuals take over and this creates
factionalism. This creates moral decay.
This creates lawlessness. This creates
corruption.
Right? So does does this make sense now?
A yes.
>> Sorry, I still don't understand why
homosexuality is able to form factions
while heterosexuality cannot.
>> Okay. All right. So So let me explain
this again. Okay. Oh, wait. Or or you
want to? Yes.
>> Yeah. Um because I'm thinking of the
symmetry between uh uh Inferno 6 uh was
it 16 and Paradisial 16? Because in
theory in paradigio 16, we're also
talking about factions that right
>> but I guess the core lesson that uh I
think if I remember back for uh on on
six paradigial 16 was that
>> um there was a line there was a concept
where it says like uh the the individual
should serve the family instead of the
family making that individual noble.
>> Yeah.
>> You get what I mean? So so so bringing
it back to Inferno 16, right? uh with I
I don't know if it's homosexuality or
self-indulgence of self-centeredness,
but the the idea of uh you know cases
where I observe people with homosexual
tendencies tending to rise is because
they are they're able to harness the
power of the group to serve them.
>> Yes.
>> Right. Uh uh uh by by you know by by
withholding participation. So I in my
mind that that kind of makes sense and
is elegant.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Okay. So, so, so
let let me explain another way. Okay.
Um,
homosexuals are able to have multiple
lovers. That's not a problem for them,
right?
Are do you understand this this idea?
>> I don't understand because I feel like
like love is still lovely.
>> Okay. So, with heterosexuals, if you
love someone, you get married, right?
A a marriage is a compact between two
people and only two people. And if you
bring another person like like like a
mistress, well
um that breaks the the bond. Do you
understand? Uh yes.
>> I think for female homosexuals and
lesbians, they are more committed to
one-on-one relationship. But if it's
like male homosexuals, then it's
completely different. So it's a
different game. It's like you could have
multiple lovers and that is okay. So I
think that's why it's hard for you as a
girl to understand it.
>> Yeah. Okay. All right. So So yeah. Okay.
Thank you. Yes. Yes. If you're a woman
and someone loves you, right, you want
that you want that to be a one-on-one
thing, right? Whereas if you're a man,
you don't really care. So So you'll be
able to have like a large
um network of male lovers. And again,
like if you just like look at any
history, whether it's Washington DC or
Hollywood, I mean, like it's pretty
common. Okay. Uh yes.
>> And I think it's uh not just about like
being being a homosexual. It's about
like having a same vision so you can
like uh assemble a group of people
together like secret society and it
follows the same logic, right? To to
infiltrate the bureaucracy.
>> Yeah. No, I again I don't think the
intention is evil. I just think they
they want to they just want to like be
homosexuals, right? Because that's what
gives them happiness. But to do so
because they're so heavily persecuted by
others, they have no choice but to be
become a secret society. Okay. Um uh
yes.
>> And I also have heard that uh in
homosexual society uh the people they
got their some people they got their
right to have more lover but some people
they don't have the right to get and
some people play in the male role and
some people play in the female role. So
this kind of hierarchy order in the uh
some homosexual uh you know society like
that. Yeah.
>> Right. Yes. Okay. Yes.
>> Um, yeah. So, well, we're talking about
like back then gay marriage or
homosexuality was more like persecuted,
but nowadays more accepted, right? So
for example like when you look at Tel
Aviv or like this like where for example
also the middle class people are more
open and homosexual and they're not
really like about taking power or like
trying to overthrow society
>> right so so so this is what Donn is
saying here
um as rising society's focus on
expanding society on family on marriage.
A lot of social policies are centered
around the family. Okay. But once a
society has become decadent, then the
elite don't really care about society.
All they care about is indulging in
their own desires
and they want to feel good about
themselves and they really don't care
about the impact on society. Um so so if
you look at today yes there is openness
and acceptance but at the same time the
level of political corruption it is out
it is just out it is just incredible the
level of political corruption. Okay not
just like you look at Washington DC
where the Trump family is just engaged
in the most egurious
uh corruption and they're not even
hiding it. Okay? They're just open about
it. They're like, you know, if you give
me if you give me if you're in prison,
you give me like, you know, $10 million,
I'll let you out. It's open. Okay. Now,
let me let me ask you this. Okay. Let's
imagine Donald Trump, he's kicked out of
office in 2028. The the Democrats come
in. What are they going to do?
>> Uh, yes.
>> Put him in prison.
>> They'll probably put him in prison. And
then what? What are they going to do?
>> It's going to purge his family.
>> Excuse me.
>> It's going to purge his family. purge
the Trump.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. They they'll go
after Trump, but then what are they
going to do?
>> Ask for a ransom.
>> They'll probably be even worse. Okay. Do
you understand?
They they'll they'll say, you know, like
when you come in, we'll clean house and
we'll restore
the sanctity of the American Republic.
No, they're not. When they come in,
they'll engage engage even more
corruption.
Okay. So, so that's what Don is is
saying here like when the elite lose
their sense of responsibility for the
people then society just becomes loses
its anchor it just goes into freef fall
okay and um yes I mean I don't want to
say homosexuality is bad but um the
reason why people kept homosexuality
hidden before was they had pay they they
had to be they had to pay virtue to the
family, right? They had to pretend at
least the family was important. Yeah. I
mean, like they probably had these
homosexual affairs on the side, but at
least they were hypocrites. At least
they made a point of like playing to the
public perception, right? Yes.
>> Yeah. What about LGBT? Do you think
Danting will agree with that or do you
think
>> it's the same thing as homosexuality,
right? There's no difference.
uh you know it's the same idea. It's
it's the same sense of like
self-indulgence
and what matters is my own pleasure, my
own happiness and I really don't care
the impact on society. Okay, does it
make sense guys? All right. So, so again
what we're doing is we're trying to
um logically come to understand uh
Dante's uh cosmology. Okay. All right.
So um but again I want to thank you guys
for raising questions for doubting for
challenging because this helps us as a
group to think much more deeper. Okay so
Dante implants in the mind comment a lot
of paradoxes which allows us to think
deeper and we are we are able to arrive
at the truth through uh exploration and
through debate. Okay. Uh yes,
>> I think one thing that would be worth
exploring is to actually interview, you
know, maybe people around us who are
homosexuals. Um you know, what what what
exactly Dante is trying to convey here
because I I guess at the end of the day,
all punishment is self punishment,
right? It it it's it's a it's a it's an
internal loop, right? I think the
answers would be in in in in those
individuals just asking just, you know,
maybe trying to learn more.
>> Okay. Um, so,
um, a couple comments. Um,
uh, first of all, this is being live
streamed
and we need to be conscious of
protecting people's privacy. Okay. Um,
uh, but yes, I I think that if we were
to share our stories more, this would
help the discussion, but the constraint
is that this is being um live stream. Uh
and the other thing is that because it's
being live streamed and because we're
dealing with different contexts, we're
in China, we're broadcasting a global
audience. Um you know, we are at the
Yale Beijing center. Uh we need to be
conscious of the cultural sensitivities
of each c of of each place. Okay. Um
um and
um look, censorship is a reality in this
world.
Ideally, we we be free to complete
explore and that's what leads to
greatest truth. But we're living in a
time of massive censorship and where
you'll be judged uh unfairly for things
you say. Okay? Uh this is a different
time. I mean, when I was growing up,
when we were in college, like like free
speech was the primary
ideal like like it's something like you
don't you don't do that to people like
you you may disagree with them, but you
don't censor them. that that that was
that was what was considered a sin. Now
it's this very common practice to cancel
people for things they they they say
people are judged very harshly. Yes.
>> Um so I actually had this question
yesterday as well. So what about those
people who purposefully chose not to
have kids cuz in some ways they're also
blocking social mobility just like the
homosexuals in a certain way but they're
not depicted in like anywhere in the
divine comedy. So,
>> and and how would Donnie feel about
these people who don't have kids?
>> Like, if they chose not to have kids, I
feel like in some ways it's like similar
to like the homosexual. So, I feel like
he should have like a similar feeling.
>> Well, okay. Okay. Well, here's here's a
question then. Okay. In the Catholic
Church, what kind of people are most
revered?
Yeah.
Yeah. Right. That's a problem. Monks and
Yeah. Yeah. Go ahead.
>> And also you have to take in the time
back then in the 14th century there's
probably no condoms and so there's no
way like you said that I want to choose
to be not having kids if I'm married.
It's not usually an option unless you're
a priest. Obviously you're not married
in the first place.
>> So then for Dante it's hard to
understand they are married couples who
choose and you know could not have kids.
So then that's why maybe it's not in the
you know listed here. It's not an option
back then.
>> And also like if you're a woman, okay,
if you had a free will, you probably
would not want to get married. Why?
>> That doesn't know. Yeah,
>> because if you give birth, there's
one/ird of a chance or more that you're
going to die.
>> Yeah. Guys, do you understand how how
awful it was to be a woman back then?
There were no condoms. There was no
hygiene. There were no hospitals.
Onethird chance of dying in childbirth,
right? It's like suicide.
>> And like quite honestly
>> like you're expected to give birth a
lot, right? It's like the first one hit
you.
>> It's very common for a woman to die at
child birth at this time. So including
including Beatric. Beatric died giving
birth at 24. At 24, right? So so so
yeah. Okay. Uh any more questions before
we we move on? Yes. So in my in my
research of Arisatilian
tieios like have you just I missed it
yesterday afternoon. Did you discuss the
tieios? Like everything has a specific
purpose in life. And I see I see the
difference between lust and
homosexuality because they're on
separate levels as being like lust.
You're focusing on one thing one thing
perhaps the correct thing, right?
Because if if uh uh Augustine and Dante
would be saying um the purpose of of of
a relationship would be reproduction and
marriage.
If you're lusting, that could happen.
You're just wanting it in maybe an
incorrect way or too much. But in
homosexuality, the tio is off because
there there is no reproduction that
could happen. And so I see this as
or I don't see this. I'm I'm reading
scholars who are pointing out that
homosexuality is just simply enough an
incorrect tios and lust is a correct
tio, but at an incorrupt incorrect
proportion. And so all of this extra
stuff might be fine and social. It just
seems like muddying the waters where
Aristoilian
uh understanding would simplify it.
>> Okay. So that you bring up Aristotle and
that that's a very interesting analysis.
At this time Aristotle is very popular
and Dante would have known Aristotle. He
would have known the idea of tilos. The
idea of tilos is purpose right? You come
here for purpose and you achieve
happiness by achieving your your tilos.
And on that idea, Dante would agree. But
um
but for Aristotle, Tilos is really about
fulfilling your social responsibility.
Whereas for Dante, he's very much an
individualist,
meaning like for Tilos is about
fulfilling yourself.
Okay. Now um their students would say
there's really no difference but uh for
Dante there is a major difference right
one the difference is uh between
fulfilling people's expectation of your
toss as to number two really
understanding your toss and achieving
your toss okay and so basically what the
students say is look society knows
what's best and if society says you
should go have children then that's your
tilos
But what Donna would say, no, no, no.
You trust your intuition, right? If your
tilos is like I I want to write poetry
for the rest of my life and I I don't
want to have children, then you should
just follow your your intuition. Okay.
So So that's that's the difference. But
but but absolutely right. Aristotle is
very important at this state at this
time in history. All right. Any more
comments or questions? This is great by
the way. Um and it really shows uh your
depth of understanding has radically
improved over the past few days. Yes.
uh like uh previously you said that uh
any any great art in the history uh
whether it's uh Homer or uh divine
comedy was often created by one single
person right and uh and is uh often
drived by the strong will and and uh but
like I think uh like go back to the
question of about like self-indulgence
um but like There also can be a
like those narcissist can also hold a
strong will right while being like uh
self-indulgent.
Uh so what separates
a a artist like sacred inwardness with
uh to a to a narcissist?
>> Okay. All right. So yesterday I I I I
did say the problem of homosexuality is
self-indulgence. And I recognize that is
incorrect. Okay. That's why I went back
and I suffered and I came up with a new
understanding. And in this new
understanding, the problem isn't
self-indulgence. The problem is
factionalism. Okay. So, Donnie is not
saying in self-indulgence is a problem.
Prize is a problem. Self-indulgence is
not a problem. You need a you need a bit
of self-love. You need a bit of ego if
you are if you are to achieve or or
create a a great piece of art. Okay. All
right. All right. Great. Any more
questions before we start? Okay. Let
let's let's start k uh inferno 21
kanto 21.
We came along from one bridge to another
talking of things my comedy is not
concerned to sing. We held fast to the
summit then stayed our steps to spy the
other clft of Melabj and other vain
laments. I saw that it was wonderfully
dark as in the arsenal of the Venetians.
All winter long a stew of sticky pitch
boils up to patch their sick and
tattered ship that cannot sail. Instead
of v voyaging some build new keels, some
tow and tar the ribs of hole worn out by
too much journeying. Some hammer at the
prow, some at the stern, and some make
orars and some braid ropes and cords.
One mens the jib and other the main
sail. So not by fire, but by the art of
God below there boiled a thick and terry
mass that covered all the banks with
clamminess.
I saw it, but I could not see within it.
Nothing was visible but boiling bubbles,
the swelling of the pitch, and then it
settled.
And while I watched below attentively,
my guide called out to me, "Take care.
Take care." And then from where I stood,
he drew me near. I turn around as one
who's impatient to see what he should
shun, but is dashed down beneath the
terror he has undergone, who does not
stop his flight, and yet would look, and
then in back of us I saw a black demon
as he came racing up the cracks. Ah, he
was surely barbarous to see, and how
relentless seemed to me his ax. His
wings were open, his feet were light
across his shoulder, which was sharp and
high. He had slung a sinner upward from
the thighs. In front the demon gripped
him by the ankles. Then from our bridge
he called, "Ola Branche, I've got an
elder of St. Svita for you. Shove this
one under. I'll go back for more. His
city is well furnished with such stores.
There everyone's a grafter but Bonuro.
And there for cash they'll change a no
to yes."
He threw the center down that wheeled
along the stony cliff. No mastiff ever
been unleashed with so much haste to
chase a thief. The sinner plunged, then
surfaced, black with pitch. But now the
demons from beneath the bridge shouted.
The sacred face has no place here. Here
we swim differently than in this circ.
If you don't want to feel our grappling
hooks, don't try to lift yourself above
that ditch. They pricricked him with a
100 prongs and more. and then taunted
here. One dances undercover, so try to
grab your secret graft below.
>> Okay. All right. So, we are in the
circle of fraud where everyone lies and
deceives and steals. Uh and here this is
the punishment for the for garafters,
people who engage in corruption and
graft.
And um the example being used is this um
priest who who obviously is engaging in
simmon. And um the punishment is to
basically fester in boiling uh in a in
boiling excrement. And some of them feel
the pain so much that they try to
escape. They try to escape and then the
demons catch them and tear them and tear
them apart. And that that is their uh
punishment. Okay. All right. Uh, let's
keep on going.
>> Line 55.
The demons did the same as any cook who
has his urchins forced the meat with
hooks deep down into the pot that it not
float. Then my good master said to me,
"Don't let those demons see that you're
here. Take care to crouch behind the
cover of a crag.
No matter what offense they offer me,
don't be afraid. I know how these things
go. I'll had to face such processes
before. When this was said, he moved
beyond the bridge head, and on the sixth
embankment, he had need to show his
imperturbility.
With the same frenzy, with the bruhaha
of dogs, when they beset a poor wretch,
who then stops dead in his tracks as if
to beg. So from beneath the bridge, the
demons rushed against my guide with all
their prongs. But he called out, "Can't
you forget your savagery before you
tried to maul me? Just let one of your
troops step forward, hear me out, and
then decide if I'm to be hooked." At
this they howed, "Let Melakota go." And
one of them moved up, the other stayed.
And as he came, he asked, "How can he
win?" "A Malakota, do you think I've
come?" my master answered him. already
armed as you can see against your optics
obstacles without the will of God and
helpful fate. Let us move on. It is the
will of heaven for me to show this wild
way to another. At this the pride of
Malakakota fell as prong dropped his
feet. He told his fellows, "Since that's
the way things stand, let us not wound
him." My guide my guide then spoke to
me. Oh you who crouch bent low among the
bridges splintered rocks, you can feel
safe and now return to me. Okay. So, um
Dante and Virgil see these demons. Okay.
And in this
stage in the story, there are some
things that are unusual.
What What's unusual about the story?
What is it that that that that's
happening that didn't really happen
before?
What strikes you as strange in the story
so far?
as
yes that demons are the one punishing
whereas before it was like natural
causes.
>> Yes. Okay. Yes. So so f first of all um
demons are in charge of of the
punishment. Uh yes. Okay. But there's a
bigger surprise here and this didn't
really happen before.
Where's Dante?
He's hiding, right? This hasn't happened
before.
This is the first time that that Donnie
is hiding.
So, what does this tell us about the
emotional state of Virgil?
How's he feeling right now?
Why would why would Donnie hide here but
not elsewhere? Right. They went to the
city of this and that this was this was
also ruled by fallen angels. But D
didn't hide. Yes.
>> I think he starts to lose trust in
Virgil and he's afraid of Virgil can't
control the demons that he used to.
>> But but who told Donn to hide?
>> Virgil?
>> It was Virgil who told D to hide, right?
So that doesn't make much sense. But
keep on going. What's going on here?
Yeah, Virgil's afraid. It's not D who's
afraid. It's Virgil who's afraid. Okay.
And so, how does Virgil respond to his
own fear?
What what are ways in which you you you
can respond with fear to fear to your
own fear? How is Virgil responding to
his fear?
>> By all fright. So either you fight it or
you run away from it. So he kind of
fights it. He kind of stands up and be
like, "Hey, bring one guy and talk to me
and let's see if we can figure this
out."
>> Right. Okay. Yes.
>> Well, by projecting his fear onto
someone else, he can he kind of can deal
with it. [clears throat] Well, because
Virgil, I don't know. How can he even
feel fear if he's not alive?
If he's not even
it's not what I I don't understand.
>> So he doesn't have a body but he still
has emotions. Right.
Right. Otherwise how could you be
punished in hell if you have absolutely
no emotions? You can't feel any
punishment. Right. So you still have
emotions. Right.
How does how does Virgil choose to
confront the demons? Right? Virgil's
afraid of the demons. So what does he do
to
deal with the demons?
>> The there's a higher power protecting
me. So don't touch me.
>> Yeah. Right. He's flexing. He's being
arrogant. Right. So to deal with his
fear, he's choosing to be proud and
arrogant before the demons.
Okay? And the demons sense his pride and
they uh lower themselves to
uh Virgil. Okay? Does that make sense
the logic here? Virgil's afraid and he
doesn't really know how to control
control the situation. So his first
instinct is to protect Dante.
Uh and then Virgil goes up and confronts
the demons and flexes, right? Says, you
know, I'm much stronger than you. Obey
me. And demon's like, fine, whatever.
Okay. Right.
Why should we we be suspicious here of
of what's going on?
Yes,
>> I have a question because uh I remember
you said uh the vir should be master of
the of the hell but why he just freed of
demon in this case
>> because you're doing factions in hell
right the thing about hell is like it's
like Italy where no one's really in
charge and no one's fighting each other
because of their pride right
okay so he he's master or certain parts
of hell, but not all parts of hell. As
as you go deeper into hell, he loses
control. Okay. All right. Okay.
Like
if you're a demon
and someone is flexing at you, what what
should your response be?
Yeah. Like I can punch you out, man.
Right. So So this is very suspicious.
You know, again, this is a paradox. And
whenever there's a paradox, it forces us
to think deeper, right? Why are the
demons being so obedient, right? Why are
the demons luring themselves? And and so
what what do you think the answer is?
We are in the circle of fraud, guys.
Deception, right? Do you understand?
Okay, that's that's what these demons
are. They are engaged in deception. They
enjoy deception,
right? Does that make sense? And if you
are this demon and you're a head demon
and you love deception, you think you
can deceive Virgil. Why?
Okay. Okay. So let us
um think of an example from real life.
Okay. All right. Um
yes.
>> Because by uh by trick by trickering
Virgil, you basically mocking God.
>> No, no, no, no. I'm trying to figure out
how he figured out you can trick Virgil.
Uh yes.
>> Virgil's in is in limbo. So he's in a
relatively speaking much nicer place
than these pe these guys.
>> Okay. All right. All right. So we don't
want to overthink things. Okay. The
solution has to be simple and elegant.
So let's just think think of an example
where you know you're with your friend.
Okay. And maybe you know you go to
uh and I'm just making this up. Okay.
you go to you go to Turkey for vacation
and your friend
um you know may maybe maybe your friend
lives in Turkey and you're going to go
visit your friend in Turkey right and
your friend in Turkey wants to show you
a good time so then your friend takes
you to this uh bazaar the store and he's
like you know like oh I I know how to
haggle right do you understand the logic
here right
>> and what's a Show show stop show stop
show stop show stop show stop show stop
show owning going to do he he's going to
see like you're friend right you don't
want to lose face you want to show how
much in control you are right doesn't
make sense and so you recognize oh it's
this arrogance it's this pride I can
take advantage of doesn't make sense
okay so so again the thing thing about
literature is you can always apply it to
real life and it has to make sense
Okay. Does does that make sense, guys?
All right. So, the demon recognizes, hm,
Virgil thinks he's got God in his side,
right? Well, I can probably rip him off
now, right? Because he's so he's so
arrogant. He's so full of himself. It's
easier to trick arrogant people than
it's trick humble people. Okay? Does
that make sense? All right. Uh let's
let's keep on going.
Line 88.
My guide then spoke to me. Oh you who
crouch bent low but among the bridg's
splintered rocks. You can feel safe and
now return to me. At this I moved and
quickly came to him. The devils had
edged forward. All of them. I feared
that they might fail to keep their word.
Just so I saw the infantry where they
mar when they marched out under safe
conduct from Caprona. They trembled when
they passed their enemies. My body
huddled closer to my guide. I did not
let the demons out of sight. The looks
they cast at us were less than kind.
>> How How is Dante feeling right now?
>> Scared.
>> Yeah, he's probably like, "This doesn't
this doesn't feel right." Okay. You
know, you're at this bizaar and it's
clear the shop owner is going to rip us
off. We should be careful, right? But
your friend's like, "No, I know this
guy. Okay. We're like we we're like, you
know, we went to school together. He's
going to give me face. He's going to
give us a best deal. Okay.
All right. So, Dante is afraid. Um, Kim,
line 100.
They bent their hooks and shouted to
each other. And shall I give it to him
on the rump? And all of them replied,
"Yes, let him have it." But Malakakota,
still in conversation with my good
guide, turned quickly to his squadron
and said, "Be still, Scar Scar Leone,
still." To us, he said, "There's no use
in going much farther on this ridge
because the sixth bridge at the bottom
there is smashed to bits. Yet, if you
two still want to go ahead, move up and
walk along this rocky edge nearby,
another which will form a path." Five
hours from this hour yesterday, 1,266
years passed since that roadway was
shattered here. I'm sending 10 of mine
out there to see if any sinners lift
this head for air. Go with my men.
There's no malice in them.
>> Okay, so he's saying that keep don't
keep on going because a bridge was
destroyed by Jesus when he came to hell.
There's another way. I'm going to send
10 of my men with you. And again, just
the idea that he says there is no malice
in them, like don't do evil. You should
be careful, right? Like we won't trick
you, okay? We mean you no harm. That's
probably a sign you should be careful.
But again, Virgil is too arrogant to
recognize this. Okay, keep on going.
>> Line 118.
Step forward, Alakino and Kabrina. He
then began to say, "And you Kanyazzo and
Babaricia, who can lead the 10? Let it
be and Drainato and Tusky Cherato and
Rafia Kane and Farello and Matt
Rubicante.
Search all around the clammy stew of
pitch. Keep these two safe and sound
till the next bridge that rise without
break across the den."
A me? What is it this master that I see?
I said, "Can't we do without company? If
you know how to go, I want no escort. If
you're just as keen as usual, can't you
see how those demons grind their teeth?
Their brows are menacing. They promise
trouble. And he to [snorts] me, I do not
want you frightened. Just let them nash
away as they may wish. They do it for
the wretches boiled in pitch. They
turned around along the left bank, left
hand bank. But first each pressed his
tongue between his teeth a signal for
their leader Barbaricia and he had made
a trumpet of his ass. Okay. So um what
does Donnie do here that he's never done
before?
Yeah. Do you guys do you guys see this?
Okay. He's actually challenging Virgil
verbally. Maybe before he had before he
had his doubts, right? But he kept them
secret out of respect for Virgil. So why
is Sony doing this?
Why is Donnie challenging Virgil and
saying we really shouldn't trust these
guys, right? He's he's he's now verbally
challenging Virgil.
Why?
Excuse me.
>> He's afraid of getting tricked.
>> Okay. He's fear. Yes.
Uh what else?
>> Isn't Virgil's pride getting in the way
here? And so Dante is just like,
"Forget about getting the good deal at
the bizaar, man. Let's just let's just
go."
>> Exactly. Right. And why would you do
that?
>> I mean, I would do it because of
frustration. I would just be like,
"There's a simpler way. You're making
this more complex than it needs to be."
Why Dante does it, I don't.
>> Okay.
Okay. Uh, yes. Well, just his intuition
maybe says it. So,
>> right. But but again, we've been reading
the Divine Comedy, and there are lots of
cases where Donna doesn't really feel
right about this about the situation,
but doesn't really speak up,
right?
He's afraid, but he doesn't really speak
up. And now he not only does he speak
up, but he's actually challenging Virgin
says like here your intuition may not be
correct. Why would he do that?
Yes. I think it's basically his literary
work is trying to show that maybe he's
hinting that he could be better than
Virgil because he's the meek and human
like the humble one. So he could see the
truth more simply than Virgil. So he's
trying to show that this is the turning
point where I will be, you know, the
better poet or the better person in the
situation.
>> Okay. All right. Let's think think of an
example. Okay. So, you're in school and
this is primary school and there's a
classmate and this classmate, you know,
is cheating. Okay? Now, there there's
going to be some classmates who are
going to go up to up to him and says,
"Hey, I saw you cheating. Don't cheat."
Okay? There'll be some other classmates
who just ignore this. What's the
difference?
Who would go up to the cheating student
and says, "Look, you're cheating and the
teacher teacher is going to catch you,
so maybe you should stop."
In what instance would you Yes,
>> it could be as an act of love. When you
>> It's an act of love. Do you understand?
It's an act of love because you're
putting yourself at risk as well, right?
you're you're putting yourself when you
tell your friend, "Let's get out of
here." Right? Not only are you angering
the your friend's pride, but you might
piss off the the shop owner as well.
It's an act of love. You're putting
yourself at risk. Okay? Does that make
sense? It's not an act of like, "I know
more than you, Virgil."
Right? You can't know more than Virgil
because Virgil is your guide in hell.
It's an act of like Virgil,
uh, I love you and, uh, I want to
protect you as you're protecting me.
Okay. So, what this is telling us is
that what this really what this journey
really is, it's it's a journey into love
where Ver Don before had tremendous
respect for Virgil, but now they're just
becoming like very close because all
these adventures they're having in at in
um in hell, right?
Um does that make sense guys? And so
this is this so what's really important
to understand is not just the cosmology,
not just understand um dynastyology, but
really understand that this ultimately
um a journey um and a love story between
Dante and Virgil. Okay. So there is this
there's this conflict between the two,
but there's also real deep affection
between the two and it's very much real.
Okay. and and we know what's going to
happen. We know that eventually they'll
have to uh part. Okay. But the idea is
to create so much affection in us for
Virgil and Dante that when they do part,
we we we cry with them when they do
part. Okay. Does that make sense? All
right. I guess she had said something
that I wanted to build off of. Dante the
poet. So there's three Dantes. Dantes
the poet sat down to write this
recollection to get to explain faith,
hope, and love. But I guess they could
all be unified as capital T truth. And
he's in the realm of liars, right? And
so essentially he would be like the
longer that we stay here in the realm of
liars, they're ruining my poem of truth,
right? So let's let's get out of the lie
realm because I'm I'm transcribing
truth,
>> right? Okay. So that's an interesting
interpretation. And um I would disagree
uh because
why would why is it important for Dante
to journey into hell,
right? Because because why is Donnie
talking to these souls that are being
punished?
To
>> learn to see,
>> right? But but then what?
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> Because it's the way to paradise.
>> Um it's Yeah, it's it's the way to
paradise. But remember when Virgil and
Donnie are talking, right? Virgil says,
"Go talk to that guy." And then and then
the soul's like, "I don't want to talk
to you. And then Virgil's like, "You
should talk to him because
what what does Virgil say?
What can Donnie do for them?
Why should they talk to him? Talk to
him?" Yes.
>> Um, go back to the world and talk about
the consequences of sins.
>> Exactly. Okay. Donnie is going to record
this. So, it's very important for Donnie
to experience as much as he can in hell.
It's not about escaping hell. It's about
truly understanding hell to share with
other people. Okay? And this is the path
to truth. Uh not to avoid something but
to experience it for yourself
and then that way that heightens your
understanding. Okay. All right. Uh let's
uh keep on going. This is count 20. Uh
this is count 22. Okay.
Kanto 22.
Before this I've seen horsemen start to
march and open the assault and muster
ranks and seen them too at times beat
their retreat. And oh your land, oh
Aritines, I've seen rangers and raiding
parties galloping. The clash of
tournaments, the rush of joust. Now done
with trumpets, now with bells, and now
with drums, and now with signs from
castle walls, with native things, and
with imported wear. But never yet have I
seen horsemen, or seen infantry, or ship
that sails by signal of land, or star
moved to so strange a bugle. We made our
way together with 10 demons. Ah, what
ferocious company, and yet in church
with saints, with roers in the tavern.
But I was all intent upon the pitch to
seek out every feature of the pouch and
of people who were burning in it. Just
as the dolphins do when with arched back
they signal to the seaman to prepare for
tempest that their vessel may be spared.
So here from time to time to ease his
torment. Some sinners showed his back
above the surface then hit more quickly
than a lightning flash. And just as on
the margin of a ditch frogs crouched
their snouts alone above the water so as
to hide their feet and their plump
flesh. So here on every side these
sinners crouched but faster than a
flash. When barbaricia drew near they
plunged beneath the boiling pitch.
I saw my heart still shutters and recall
one who delayed just at just as at times
a frog is left behind while others dive
below with graphic who was closest to
him then hooked him by his pitch and
tangled locks and hauled him up. He
seemed to me an otter. By now I knew the
names of all those demons. I'd paid
attention when the fiends were chosen.
I'd watch as they stepped forward one by
one. Oh, Rubicante, see you set your
talents right into him so you can flay
his flesh so that those cursed ones cry
out together.
And I, my master, if you can find out
what is the name of that unfortunate
Roose fallen victim who to his enemies.
My guide, who then drew near that
sinner's side, asked him to tell his
birthplace. He replied, "My homeland was
the kingdom of Naare. My mother who had
had me by a wastel of himself and his
possessions had placed me in the service
of the Lord." Then I was in the
household of the worthy kings of Tibol.
There I started taking graft with this
heat I pay reckoning for that. And
Cherato, from whom smouthe right and
left two tusks like a wild hogs, then
let him feel how one of them could
mangle. The mouse had fallen in with
evil cats, but Barbaricia clasped him in
its arms and said, "Stand off there
while I fork him fast,
and turning toward my master," then he
said, "Ask Con if you would learn some
more from him before one of the others
dust him in."
>> Okay, stop. Okay. All right. So, um,
let's think about this. This is an
unusual punishment because it gives the
people here an opportunity to escape,
right? It's not like they're locked in
place. It's like, you know, there's a
boiling pitch, the boiling lake, and you
can always escape it, right? Why would
this be a fitting punishment for people
who engage in graft?
Yes. Go ahead.
In graft, they take resources and things
away from people who should have them,
>> right? Okay. And so why would this be a
fitting punishment for them?
Huh?
>> Uh, yes.
>> Maybe because it's doing that is so
addicting that they can't stop doing it,
>> right? Okay. So, there's a compulsion to
them. Yes. Right. They have to steal.
They have to engage in grab. Yes. Okay.
That's part part of it. Yes.
>> Yeah. The mechanism of it. If you steal
something, you can always at every part
of the journey, you can always decide to
to turn back and give it give it back,
you know, return whatever you stole.
>> Why do people engage in graft? What's
the mentality of people who engage in
graft?
Right?
Why do they steal? What what's your
mentality?
>> Maybe it's covereting of what others
have that you don't have, so you want to
have it.
>> Then why is this not greed?
What's going on here? What what's the
mentality? Why do they engage in graft?
Uh yes.
Oh yeah. You mean stealing, right? I
think stealing is kind of thing that you
want to get something uh and also you
can get much more benefit from it. But
there's no punishment. There's nothing
good uh nothing bad there. So that's why
people when they just like to steal,
they just stick to steal something. It's
it's really hard to give it up. Yeah.
>> Uh so yeah, go ahead.
>> Yeah. Well, also when you steal, you
decide that this thing that you're
stealing is more deserving for you than
the owner. Like you say like in your in
this action like I deserve this and the
owner doesn't really.
>> But why why do you deserve it?
>> Well, maybe pride.
Okay.
Anyone else? Yes. At the back.
>> I feel like for greed, you are kind of
more focusing on like a specific thing.
For example, like money and whatever,
but then stealing you're kind of like
stealing anything.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Like a lot of a variety of stuff.
>> But what is graph? You're stealing from
who?
>> Graft has to come from a position of
power.
>> Okay. So the person here right he
becomes a servant to a powerful lord and
then he starts to steal from this
powerful lord. Why is he doing that?
Yes.
>> Because the Lord is at a better
financial position.
>> Yeah. But then the Lord's being generous
to him, right? So why would you steal
from him?
>> I guess you you don't respect the Lord.
You don't love the Lord. But yeah, but
why don't you respect the Lord?
>> You reject the inherent hierarchy in
your relationship.
>> Okay. Uh yes. Uh maybe because just like
you you you are in the Chin dynasty and
they just try to uh steal something from
emperor because they think this they
deserve they deserve to have it because
they just pay tribute to the emperor all
the time. So
>> okay. So, so let's let's think of like a
most common example of graph. Okay,
which is the accountant, right? So,
you're a rich person. You have an
accountant and for accounting tricks,
that person is able to steal a lot of
money from you. What's the mentality
mentality of that person?
Exactly. I I'm going to get away with
this. Right. Exactly. Right. It's not
that I'm better than you. I like I I get
I can get away with this. I'm smarter
than you. That's what graft is. I'm
gonna get away with this. There's no
punishment. I'm so sneaky. I'm so
clever. I can get away with this. So why
would this punishment be fitting for
these people?
Okay, they are in the boiling pitch.
That kind of sucks. They escape and
they're caught by demons who do what to
them?
>> Outsmart them.
>> These demons literally tear them apart,
right? Which is the worst punishment?
The second one. Right. So, it's kind of
silly where look, if you just stay where
you are, if you just stay in that boring
pitch, it kind of sucks, but it's a lot
better than being like, you know, torn
to pieces by demons, right?
But they can't help themselves. They're
like, "No, I have to escape." Because
they're they're always like, "I'll get
away." Right? But like, we know for a
fact you're not going to get away
because this is hell. This is God's
perfect justice. There's no way you're
going to escape hell. But for the reason
they're like, "No, I will escape this
time even though for the past 10 million
times I was caught by the demon and and
you know destroyed." Okay.
Okay. Does that make sense? Okay. Yes.
>> Wait. So when they're torn to pieces,
they the bodies get back together or
>> uh Yeah. So they're torn to pieces, then
they resurrect in in a boiling pitch.
>> Then they do it again.
>> And then something happens. and they do
it again. This happens like for all
eternity. Okay. So, it's it's it's it's
almost like this compulsion where they
think I'll get away this time, right?
I'll I won't get caught this time. I'll
be so sick this time. But it's
absolutely pointless.
Okay. Does that make sense? All right.
Keep on going.
>> Line 64.
at which my guide now tell among the
sinners who hide beneath the pitch are
any others Italian and he I've just left
one who was nearby there and would I
wear still covered by the pitch as he is
hidden for then I'd have no fear of hook
or talon and Liby said we've been too
patient and with his grapple grabbed him
by the arm and ripping carried off a
hunk of flesh but Dragunato also looked
as if to grab his legs at which their
captain wheeled and threatened all of
them with raging looks when they'd grown
somewhat less tumultuous without delay.
My guide asked of that one who had his
eyes still fixed upon his wound. Who was
the one you left to come ashore? And
luckily, as you just said before, he
answered, "Fragomita of Galura, who was
a vessel fit for every fraud. He had his
master's enemies in his in hand, but
handled them in ways that pleased them
all. He took their go gold and smoothly
let them off as he himself says and in
other matter matters he was a sovereign
not a petty swindler. His comrade there
is Don McKlly Zank of Logodoro and their
tongues are never too tired to talk of
their sardinia
me see that one there who grinds his
teeth. If I were not afraid I'd speak
some more but he's getting set to
scratch my scarf. and their great
marshall facing Farfarel who was so hot
to strike he rolled his eyes said get
away from there you filthy bird if you
perhaps would like to see her here that
sinner terrified began again Lombards or
Tuscans I can fetch you some but let the
melibbron stand aside so that my
comrades may not fear their vengeance
remaining in this very spot I shall
although alone make seven more appear
when I have whistled as has been our
custom when on one of us has managed to
get out.
>> Okay, so Donnie and Virgil wants to meet
more of these sinners
and uh the sinner says, "Well, they're
all in hiding." And the demons are like,
"Uh, let's just start tearing this guy
apart because that's what we enjoy
doing." And the sinner's like, "No, no,
no. If you leave me alone, I I'll trick
seven more to appear before you."
Everyone's in hiding. So, so if you
demons just hide yourself, then I will
tell them to come out and then you can
catch seven more people to apart. Okay.
So, this is the circle of fraud, circle
of deception.
We should be wary of every of everything
people do here. Okay. All right. Uh,
keep on going.
>> Line 106. At that, Kyato lifted up his
snout and shook his head and said, "Just
listen to that trick by which he thinks
he can dive back." To this, he who was
rich in artifice replied, "Then I must
have too many tricks if I bring greater
torment to my friends. This was too much
for Alino, and despite the others," he
cried out, "If you dive back, I should
not gallop after you, but beat my wings
above the pitch. We'll leave this height
with the embankment as a screen. will
see if you alone can handle us. Oh you
who read here now of this new sport.
Each turned his eye upon the other
shore. He first who'd been most hesitant
before. The never in nick of time had
planted his feet upon the ground. Then
in an instant he jumped and freed
himself from their commander. At this
each demon felt the prick of guilt and
most he who had led his man to blunder.
So he took off and shouted, "You are
caught." But this could help him little.
Wings were not more fast than fear. The
sinner plunged right under. The other
flying up lifted his chest. Not
otherwise. The wild duck when it plunges
precipitously when the falconers and
then exhausted thwart it flies back up.
But Calcabrina, raging at the trick,
flew after Alino. He was keen to see the
sinner free and have a brawl. And once
Darvarez had disappeared, he turned his
talons on his fellow demon and tangled
with him just above the ditch. But Alino
clawed him well. He was indeed a
full-grown kestrel, and both fell into
the middle of the boiling pond. The heat
was quick to disentangle them, but still
there was no way they could get out.
Their wings were stuck and meshed in
glue like pitch. And Barbarichia
grieving with the rest said sent forth
to fly out toward the other shore with
all their forks. And speedily enough on
this side and on that they took their
posts and toward those two stuck fast
already cooked beneath that crust. They
stretched their grappling hooks. We left
them still contending with that mess.
>> Okay. All right. So um um this sinner he
he tricks the demons right says like you
know if you leave me alone for a few
seconds I will bring in more sinners
[snorts] and the demons believe him and
then the sinner escapes and the demons
chase after him and they fall into the
pit. Okay so the there's a paradox here
right the sinner has lied to the demons
but there's a paradox. What is a
paradox? Do do you guys remember what
the paradox is? Yes.
>> The demons are punished but the sinner
is not.
>> Okay. Well, the demons are are just
being stupid, right? But but but there's
a paradox. Why do demons believe him?
There's a paradox here.
Okay. You you guys you guys probably
don't remember. Okay. But there's a rule
in hell. The rule in hell is if you're
so being punished, whatever words you
speak to Dante and Virgil
must be true.
You understand? You cannot lie to Virgil
and Dante.
That's that's the rule in hell.
But
clearly
the sinner has lied to the demons,
right?
So how how come so what's going on here?
This is a contradiction.
Okay. So let's think about this. Okay.
So the demons are saying you're lying to
us. And then he says he then the sinner
says then I must have too many tricks if
I bring greater torment to my friends.
Is this a lie?
What's he saying here?
What are you saying here?
>> Like the demons are trying to hurt Dante
and Virgil.
>> No, no, no, no, no. I'm saying what does
this line mean? Then I must have too
many tricks if I bring greater torment
to my friends.
>> Wait, let's go back. Yes. But but it's
true.
>> He's not lying to you. Okay? Do you
understand? You just read what he
writes, what he's speaking. It's not a
lie technically. You understand? It's
not a deception. Technically, you're
just misinterpreting what he's saying,
right? So, let's go back to the example
of like, you know, your friend takes you
to the bazaar, right? And the bizaar
shop owner says, "This is the best
teacup in the world." Um,
then your friend your friend's like,
"You you're lying to us." And the shop
owner says, "If I'm lying to you, then I
have no friends in the world."
It could be true. Okay? Do you
understand? If I'm lying to you, I have
no friends in the world. Right? You
interpret to say, "Okay, well then he's
not lying to me."
But it could be true, right? If I'm
lying to you, I have no friends in the
world.
You understand? And this this is what we
call sulfry, right?
Sulfestry,
right? You just think you're smarter
than everyone else. You think that you
know more than everyone else and you'll
get away with everything, so you keep on
doing it. Okay? And
so he's just playing tricks with words.
Does it make sense? So he's not lying
cuz you cannot lie in hell,
but he's engaging in sophistry. Okay.
The constructive words to make you uh to
manipulate you. Does that make sense?
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
Yes.
>> Um, how come he has the will to escape?
Do people even think of escaping or just
they think of suffering less in hell?
>> Okay. Yeah. So, it's not the will to
escape. It's a compulsion to prove
you're smarter than everyone else. It's
a compulsion to cheat other people. You
understand? But the point is all you're
doing is you're cheating yourself,
right? because all you're doing is uh
escaping into a greater punishment. You
just if you just honest and stay where
you are, you'll be fine. But you you
constantly want to escape. It's a it's
it's a addiction. Okay.
>> Right. So the people who you know, at
least accountants who steal from rich
people, it's not necessarily they need
the money. It's just like they enjoy
cheating other people. Okay. All right.
Uh count of 23.
>> Count 23.
Silent alone, no one escorting us. We
made our way. One went before, one
after, as friars's minor when they
walked together. The press and frackus
made me think of Esau, that fable where
he tells about the mouse and frog. For
near and I are not more close than are
that fable in this incident, if you
compare with care how each begins, and
then compare the endings that they
share. And even as one thought springs
from another, so out of that was still
another born which made the fear I felt
before red double.
>> Okay. Sorry. Um c can you google as
fable of the frog and the horse? Okay. I
I I don't have it I don't have it
remembered. Okay. So uh
frog and horse. Yeah. Oh, sorry. Frogen
mouse. Yes. Yes. Okay. So So can you can
you read it for for everyone? Yeah.
Story summary of uh Esop's frog and
mouse. Mouse first asks the frog for
helping help with crossing a river to
visit the frog's home. The frog agrees
but ties the mouse's leg to his own with
a reed for safety. Halfway across the
frog, motivated by by greed for the
mouse's food, tries to drown the mouse
by diving down the surface. Um, the
mouse's dead body floats to the surface,
still tied to fl to the frog. A hawk
sees the floating mouse, swoops down and
carries off both the mouse and the frog.
So, I guess the frog um being
treacherous ends up being um prey as
well for the hawk.
>> Sure. Okay. So, this applies to the
demons, right? The demons mean to uh
swindle Don and Virgil, cheat him, but
they get greedy. They want to catch more
sinners, so they fall in their own trap.
Okay. So, yeah. Okay. Uh, this one I'm
going
>> line 13. I thought because of us they
have been mocked and this inflicted so
much hurt and scorn that I'm sure they
feel deep indignation. If anger is to be
added to their malice, they'll hunt us
down with more ferocity than any hound
whose teeth have trapped a hair. I could
already feel my hair hair curl up from
fear. And I looked back attentively
while saying, "Master, if you don't
conceal yourself in me at once, they
terrify me. Those melabbr they're after
us. I so imagine them. I hear them now."
And he to me, "Were I a leed mirror, I
could not gather in your outer image
more quickly than I have received your
inner. For even now your thoughts have
joined my own in both our acts and
aspects. We are kin with both our minds.
I've come to one decision. If that right
bank is not extremely steep, you we can
descend into the other moat and so
escape from the imagined chase.
He'd hardly finished telling hit me his
plan when I saw them approach with
outstretched wings not too far of keen
on taking us. My guide snatched me up
instantly just as the mother who's waken
from war and catch a sight of blazing
flames beside her will lift her son and
run without a stop. She cares more for
the child than for herself. not pausing
even to throw on a shift. And down the
hard embankments edge, his back lay flat
along the sloping rock that closed one
side of the adjacent moat. He slid. No
water ever ran so fast along a slle to
turn the wheels of a landmill. Not even
when its flow approached the paddles, as
said my master race down that embankment
while bearing me with him upon his
chest, just like a son and not like a
companion. His feet has scarcely reached
the bed that lies along the deep below
them. Those 10 demons were on the edge
above us. But there was nothing to fear.
For that high providence that wilt the
ministers of the fifth ditch denies all
of them the power to leave it.
>> Okay, so this is almost like a Hollywood
movie now, right? It's it's it's a chase
scene where Dante and Virgil are trying
to escape the demons. the demons are
chasing them and um [clears throat]
there's a door that's closing and they
at the last minute are able to um run
for the door into safety and the door
closes on the demons. Okay, so this is
almost like a Hollywood uh chase scene.
Why is Tony writing this?
I mean, it's gratuitous because God has
already willed Dante to go to heaven,
right? So, obviously, the demons can't
actually do anything to them. They're
protected by God. So, why is Donnie
actually running the scene? Yes.
>> Maybe to show comradeship or something.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's meant to make us
understand and appreciate the growing
relationship between Virgil and Dante,
right? Because this is this is like
basically character building. It's it's
meant to develop for us and help us
understand the intimacy between Dante
and and Virgil, right? Um, an example is
let's just say you have two enemies,
right? And they hate each other. Well, I
guarantee you if you if you were to dump
these two guys who hate each other, who
want to kill each other on a on a
deserted island, they become best
friends afterwards, right? So, so that
that that's the idea here. So even
though they are rivals ultimately this
journey will make them into best
friends. Okay I keep on going.
Below that point we found a painted
people who moved about the lagging steps
in circles weeping with features tired
and defeated and they were dressed in
cloaks with cows so low they fell before
their eyes of that same cut that used to
make the clothes for Clooney's monks
outside these cloaks were gilded and
they dazzled but inside there were all
of lead so heavy that Frederick's capes
were straw compared to them a tiring
mantle for eternity we turned turn again
is always to the left along with them
intent on their sad weeping. But with
their weights that weary people paced so
slowly that we found ourselves among new
company each time we took a step at
which I told my guide, "Please try to
find someone whose name or deed I
recognized, and while we walked, be
watchful with your eyes." And one who
taken in my tuskcen speech cried out
behind us, "Stay your steps, oh you who
hurry so along the starkened air.
Perhaps you'll have from me that which
you seek, at which my guide turned to
me, saying, "Wait, and then continue
following his pace." I stopped, and I
saw two whose faces showed their minds
were keen to be with one. Both their
loath and the tight path forced them to
slow. When they came up, they looked a
sconce at me a long while, and they
uttered not a word until they turned to
one another, saying, "The throbbing of
his throat makes this seem this one seem
alive. And if they're dead, what
privilege lets them appear without the
heavy mantle?
Then they addressed me, "Tuscen, you who
come to this assembly of sad hypocrites,
do not disdain to tell us who you are."
I answered, "Where the lovely Arnold
flows, there I was born and raised in
the great city. I'm with the body I have
always had. But who are you upon whose
cheeks I see such tears distilled by
grief? and let me know what punishment
it is that glitters so." And one of them
replied, "The yellow cloaks are of a
lead so thick their heaviness makes us
the balances beneath them creek. We both
were jovial friars and Bolognese. My
name is Catalano Loringo was his and we
were chosen by your city together for
the post that's usually one man's to
keep the peace and what we were is still
to be observed around Gardingo."
I then began, "Oh friars, your your
misdeeds," but said no more, because my
eyes had caught once one crucified by
three stakes on the ground. When he saw
me, that sinner writhed all over, and he
breathed hard into his beard with size,
observing that fraat said to me, "That
one impaled there whom you see
counseledled the Pharisees that it was
prudent to let one man and not one
nation suffer. naked he has been
stretched across the path as you can see
and he must feel the weight of anyone
who passes over him like torment in this
ditch afflicts both his father-in-law
and others in that council which for the
Jews has seated so much evil.
>> Okay, so this is Caiaphas who is uh the
Pharisee
uh the high priest who condemned Jesus
to to death. Okay. And so for his
punishment, he is crucified to the
ground and everyone just walks on him.
This is the area of the hypocrites. And
the hypocrites are punished by wearing
cloaks of lead. So like their movement
is like really really slow. Okay?
They're burdened by these cloaks of
lead. So let's think about this. Why
what is hypocrisy? And why would you be
punished walking all of eternity with
cloaks of lead that are very heavy, so
heavy that it it hurts to walk?
What is hypocrisy? Why do people engage
in it? [snorts]
>> Yes.
>> It is basically saying one thing and
doing another. So you're pretending to
be better than you are. So you put off
this mask,
>> right? And and and why do you do it?
>> To show that you're better than others.
That you are airy and kind of like ah
I'm better than everybody else. I'm more
religious.
>> Okay. So what you're saying is that
hypocrites their words have no meaning
and their words can change at any time
and they are not responsive to they're
not responsible to their words. Right.
So why do they do it? Yes.
>> I think they're cheating. They just
pretend to be a higher moral stuff just
try to on the one hand get a benefit
from that and on the other they will try
to cheat others so that they'll get get
more and they don't need to be punished
and they just hide themselves from uh
yeah okay well let's say you're a
teacher okay you're telling your
students [clears throat] okay we need to
work hard and uh read a lot of books and
exercise, okay? And then your students
like a year later, they don't do
anything, but they're like, you know,
like we we want to we we want to work
hard and exercise and read a lot of
books. Why do they do that?
H
to to please me, right? And so why would
they do that?
>> Yeah. What's the motivation?
>> To benefit from
like to pretend that you're better than
who you actually are and then you're
very empty on the interior and then the
ultimate goal is to like get benefits by
kind of like pretending to be like a
better person.
>> Yeah. Absolutely. Yes. Yes. Uh yes. And
then so you're basically um you have to
wear all those lies on yourself on your
consciousness like you're like
consciously because you know you're not
actually doing what you're saying. Now
all these things that you didn't do
but you say you did they wear on you
basically.
>> Yeah. So like before you there was
nothing holding you down, right? You
could say whatever you want, you can do
whatever you want. you just choose to do
it in order just to get by. Right now,
now um you're you're now you're being
punished with this cloak of lead. Okay.
So, does that make sense? Okay. Good.
All right. Let's let's keep going.
Line 124.
Then I saw Virgil stand amazed above
that one who lay stretched out upon a
cross so squadly in his eternal exile.
and he addressed the frier in this way.
If it does not displease you, if you
may, tell us if there's some passage on
the right that would allow the two of us
to leave without our having to compel
black angels to travel to the steep to
get us out. He answered, "Closer than
you hope, you'll find a rocky ridge that
stretches from the great round wall and
crosses all the savage valleys. Except
that here it's broken, not a bridge. But
where it ruined slope along the bank and
heap up at the bottom, you can climb. My
leader stood a while with his head bent
then said, "He who hooked sinners over
there gave us a false account of this
affair."
>> So Virgil know. So Virgil recognized
he's been lied to. Okay. Like duh,
right? Uh, keep on going.
>> At which the frier in Bolognia I once
heard about the devil's many vices. They
said he was a liar and a father of lies.
And then my guide moved on with giant
stride, somewhat disturbed, with anger
in his eyes. At this I left those
overburdened spirits while following the
prince of his dear feet.
>> So why would you trust the devil?
What could lead someone to trust the
devil?
>> Pride, right? Does that make sense?
I Is there a Christian saying saying
about this?
No. Okay. All right. All right. Well,
well, yeah. All right, let's let's let's
keep on going.
>> Conto 24.
In that part of the young year, when the
sun begins to warm its locks beneath
Aquarius and nights grow shorter,
equaling the days, when horrost mimes,
the image of his white sister upon the
ground, but not for long, because the
pen he uses is not sharp. The farmer who
is short of fodder rises and looks and
sees the fields all white at which he
slaps his thigh turns back into the
house and hear and there complaints like
some poor wretch who doesn't know what
can be done and then goes out again and
gathers up new hope on seeing that the
world have changed has changed its face
in so few hours and he takes his staff
and hurries out his flock of sheep to
pasture.
So did my master fill me with dismay
when I saw how his brow was deeply
troubled. Yet then the plaster soothed
the sore as quickly. For soon as we were
on the broken bridge, my guide turned
back to me with that sweet manner I
first had seen along the mountain space.
And he examined carefully the ruin that
having picked the way we would ascend,
he opened his arms and thrust me
forward. And just as he who pers as he
labors, who's always ready for the step
ahead, so as he lifted me up toward the
summit of one great crag, he'd see
another spur, saying, "That is the one
you will grip next, but try at it first
to see if it is firm." That has no path
for those with cloaks of lead. For he
and I, he liked, I would support, could
hardly make it up from spur to spur.
And were it not that down from this
enclosure the slope was shorter than the
bank before, I cannot speak for him, but
I should surely have been defeated. But
since Malibul runs right into the mouth
of its last well, the placement of each
valley means it must have one bank high
and half the other short. So, and so we
reached at length the jutting where the
last stone of the ruined bridge breaks
off. The breath within my lungs was so
exhausted from climbing, I could not go
on. In fact, as soon as I had reached
that sore, I sat. Stone I sat.
Now you must cast aside your laziness,
my master said. For he who rests on down
on or undercovers cannot come to fame.
And he who spends his life without
renown leaves such a vestage of himself
on earth as smoke bequetss to air or
foam to water. Therefore, get up. Defeat
your breathlessness with spirit that can
win all battles if the body's heaviness
does not deter it. A longer ladder still
is to be climbed. It's not enough to
have left them behind. If you have
understood, now profit from it.
>> Okay? [clears throat] I'm sure that you
might have had a teacher. Okay? Um, some
of you might have had a teacher who has
inspired you to greatness. And what your
teacher said to you is the reason why we
are memorizing tests for like eight
hours a day is to aspire to greatness,
right? We suffer for 12 years. We lose
our soul. We lose our individuality. But
at the end of it, we will obtain
immortality because we'll get into like
Chinua or Harvard or Yale. And then
we'll be great. Okay.
What do you think of of a teacher like
that?
There's there's quite quite a few
teachers like that in China. But but
what's your impression of a teacher like
that? I mean, he's not wrong, right? He
or she's not wrong.
And there are lots of students who are
able to get into Chinua or Bea or Y or
Harvard because of a teacher like that.
But
how do you feel about about a teacher
like that? Have you had a teacher
teacher like that? And like what's your
impression? Yeah. Yes.
>> Yeah. Because as a teacher you have to
do a job well and there's no teacher who
said to students come on don't study
it's useless right. Teacher always that
you have to study better harder so that
you will get more benefit. You know the
sweet always come from come after the
bitterness. Right. So, uh, yes,
>> I literally just said that to my
students like last week and I say to
them all the time like, "Honey, you'll
get like six years of hell or 60 years
of hell." And they were like, "Just six
years." I'm like, "Okay, now work hard
for the next six years in your middle
school so you can get to a good, you
know, undergraduate school, uh, college
so that you can have more
happiness, I guess, in the future."
>> And I'm sure a lot of your students have
succeeded, right? They've gone to like
really top universities.
>> They do better. Yeah.
>> Right. right?
>> Um achieve their full potential I
suppose.
>> Right. But but but but let's hear some
other perspectives. Right. You're a
teacher, right? And you said that. Uh
yes.
>> So back then I thought it was like
completely normal and it it is what I
should be taught because of meritocracy.
But right now, I feel like we are just
kind of in like an endless trap because
after high school, you'll be told that,
okay, you'll just have to work hard for
four years and then you'll get into like
a good grad school or like you'll get a
good job. I feel like it's just kind of
like a endless circle. And I feel like
it's more of like the teachers are
unccapable of motivating their students
to like um have like an inner drive to
study hard so that they're teaching
these sorts of ideas onto their
students.
>> Do you do do you agree with w with that?
>> No. because I actually do believe in
this narrative um of if you work hard,
you go to a good school, you actually
have a better chance of getting into
like top banking, you know, or whatever
jobs that you want because they do
filter your first degree, right? And so
I I actually do believe in this
narrative. Um I think it's very Puritan,
very biblical. So the Paul is always
saying let's you know strive for the
goal that you are you know so you live
your good life so you get your reward in
heaven. It's kind of the same narrative.
>> Okay. Right. Um
>> um I use if a teacher tells me that I
know how much effort I need to put for
their class because I mean I mean this
in the sense that if a teacher is really
good at teaching and really has a love
for their subject in classes what they
say is oh my god guys chemistry is so
amazing. It's so interesting and it
really piqus my passion. So for that
class, I put in the extra effort and I
understand that that teacher understands
my passion for the subject. But if a
teacher tells me, you just need to do
this uh to to get to a good college, I
know like that class, I'm not going to
really learn anything. So, I'm just
going to put the amount of effort that's
needed for me to get an A and just
so like I guess for me um my
understanding of um education is not to
you know get that job. it's to you know
better yourself and also learning is fun
>> but if the teachers don't understand and
take that perspective I can't really
convince them that so it just um
>> okay we we understand thank you uh yes
>> yeah I think it's just not really about
the aspect of hard work I think yes
obviously you need to do work hard but
it's more about the motivation behind it
and it's easier if you're motivated
obviously to learn something that you're
interested in. So if the teacher tells
you like she said, you know, you need to
do this or like I will teach this in a
way that it makes it harder for you
because you won't like it or I'm going
to teach this in a way that you will
like it and obviously it's easier to
study
>> and so it's more about the motivation.
>> Okay. Yes.
I think log logically it makes uh sense
this way of teaching but it it just
assumes that this is the only important
thing in life because you could get say
a teacher who says well don't worry too
much but focus on you know your soul
your spirit and you know be happy with
your life and then you get two different
adults. You get one who's working in
banking, earning a lot of money, but
anti-depressants, not happy with their
life. And then you get one who didn't,
you know, work that hard, didn't make it
to that college, but maybe they still
had a family and they're happy.
>> Yes. Okay. Thank you. Yes.
>> I see this narrative as a way of
blinding yourself for better outcomes.
Same as like a horse can have the thing
on the side just to move faster. So, you
don't really see why you're doing it,
but it's just a way to have better
outcomes. So you're like, "Okay, let me
blind myself for the next like 3 years
and I know that when I open my eyes,
it's going to be just better."
>> Okay. Thank you. Yes.
>> Uh it is a white lie that has been
perpetuated from generation to
generation.
Uh it is um I think it is the purpose of
the white lie that is more important
than the content and truthfulness.
It is uh sometimes comparable to a
beautiful wrapping of a gift. You know,
it's it might be a just a wrapping, but
when you unpack it, you you still want
to, you know, look at the beautiful
wrapping and uh appreciate
uh but uh it really depend on uh the
audience.
uh uh a bad audience uh might uh you
know uh be obsessed with it and uh and
might have some you know very tragic
result.
>> Okay, good. Uh yes,
>> I think the problem with education
especially public school education in
China is that the pe the students don't
know why they're learning. They think
the reason why they are learning is
because they need to do it to get to a
good high school to get to a good
college to get to a good job. But that's
like the most boring reason for why you
learn. Like if teachers taught students
why you learn is because it's fun and
it's interesting and it's it's amazing
and it's it's actually very it's like if
you actually teach people why learning
is fun and interesting then therefore
students realize that like in life they
don't need to work towards a goal. They
can just you know strive towards
enjoying the journey.
>> Okay. Yeah. Well, it's a great
discussion, but but but you you you have
the last word. Okay, then we'll
continue. Yes. Okay. Yes.
>> Sorry, I had to put out the counter
argument that um if we prime education
to be something fun, of self-discovery,
of passion and love, you'll realize that
learning is antihuman just like
exercising like in a way it is you know
it is good for you but you know to eat
salad every day and to exercise be an
athlete you know be a great achiever
would take pain would take a bit of you
know suffering. So when everything is
fund driven and passion driven what if
you have passion for chemistry but not
for physics or like the teacher try to
invoke passion in you but it's hard
because you you are just a chemistry
person not physics or not math or
Chinese you know language arts person
then you will lose like oh then you know
physic uh chemistry is my you know
passion and that's the only thing I'm
going to learn well then the rest of it
it's like whatever then I think it's a
better to have a narrative like yeah the
other subjects are not as fun but
they're equally as important for your
future to you Yeah. So, just for some
context for those who are watching on
the live stream who do not know the
Chinese system, uh the Chinese system,
it at the end of high school, everyone
takes a comprehensive examination that
tests six subjects. So, you can have a
great love of math, but if you don't do
well in English, you're really really
screwed. Okay? It's comprehensive. So,
it's not just about passion. It's about
like discipline. You have to like do
well on all six subjects. Okay? So,
let's continue. Okay? Now, what Virgil
says to Dante is cast aside your
laziness because what what we're trying
to achieve is eternal fame. If you want
to be the greatest poet in the world,
you have to work a lot harder.
What could Virgil say instead to
motivate Dante? And it' be a lot more
effective, by the way.
Exactly right.
What is Dante doing right now? Right?
He's trying to get to Beatric. Beatric
came to Virgil and says like, I I want
to see Dante again. Bring him to me.
Right? That is what Virgil's mission is
to take Dante to Beatric. Right? So,
what Virgil should be saying to Dante is
Petus is waiting for us. Let's get there
as soon as possible. And that's going to
motivate uh Beatric D a lot more than
like, hey, everlasting fame, man. That's
what we want. Okay. So, it shows you
psychology,
the virtual psychology. Okay. And that
and that's why this is a great work of
literature because Virgil is a real
person, right? He's just he's not just a
plot device. He has his own motivations.
He has his own psychology. He has has
his own worldview. All right. All right.
Uh let's keep on going.
>> Line 58. Then I arose and showed myself
far better equipped with breath than I
had been before. Go on, for I am strong
and confident. We took our upward way
upon the ridge with crags more jagged,
narrow, difficult, and much more steep
than we had crossed before. I spoke as
we went on, not to seem weak at this. A
voice came from the ditch beyond. A
voice that was not suited to form words.
I know not what he said, although I was
already at the summit of the bridge that
crosses there, and yet he seemed to
move. I bent that I had bent downward
but my living eyes cannot see the bottom
through that dark at which I said oh
master can we reach the other belt let
us descend the wall for as I hear and
cannot understand so I see down but can
distinguish nothing. The only answer
that I give to you is doing it. He said
a just request is to be met in silence
by the by the act. We then climb down
the bridge just at the end where it runs
right into the eighth embankment. And
now the moat was plain enough to me. And
there within I saw a dreadful swarm of
serpents so extravagant in form.
Remembering them still drains my blood
from me. Let Libya boast no more about
her sands. For if she breathed kelly,
jaculi
shankers with empisbina parade. She
never showed with all of Ethiopia or all
the land that borders the Red Sea so
many such malignant pestilences. Among
this cruel and depressing swarm ran
people who were naked, terrified with no
hope of a hole or helotrope.
Their hands were tied behind by serpent.
These had thrust their head and tail
right through the loin and then were
knotted on the other side. And there a
serpent sprang with force at one who
stood upon our shore transfixing him
just where the neck and shoulders from a
knot. No o or I has ever been
transcribed so quickly as that soul
caught fire and burned and as he fell
completely turned to ashes. And when he
lay undone upon the ground, the dust of
him collected by itself and instantly
returned to what it was. Just so it is
asserted by great sages that when it
reaches its 500th year, the phoenix dies
and then is born again. lifelong. It
never feeds on grass or grain, only on
drops of incense and amum. Its final
winding sheets are nard and myrr. And
just as he who falls and knows not how,
by demons force that drags him to the
ground, or by some other hindrance that
binds man, who when he rises stares
about him, all bewildered by the heavy
anguish he has suffered, sighing as he
looks around, so did the sinner stare
when he arose. Oh, how severe it is the
power of God that as its vengeance
vengeance showers down such bloat.
My guide then asked that sinner who he
was. To this he answered, "Not long
since I reigned from Tuskanyany into
this savage mall knew that I was the
beastial life pleased me and not the
man. I'm Vani fu chief beast and the den
that suited me Pistoya and I to Virgil
tell him not to slip away and ask what
sin has thrust him here. I knew him as a
man of blood and anger."
The sinner heard and did not try to
faint but turned his mind and face
intent toward me and coloring with
miserable miserable shame. He said,
"I suffer more because you've caught me
in this the misery you see than I
suffered when taken from the other life.
I can't refuse to answer what you ask.
I'm set down so far because I robbed the
sacry of its fair ornaments and someone
else was falsely blamed for that." But
lest the sight give you too much
delight, if you can ever leave these
lands of darkness, open your ears to my
announcement here. Bistoa first will
strip herself of black, and Florence
will renew her men and manners. From
Maldi, Margaret Mars will draw a vapor
which turpet clouds will try to wrap.
The clash between them will be fierce,
impetuous. A tempest fought upon Compo
Paciano until that vapor, vicorous,
vigorous
shall crack the mist and every white be
struck by it. And I have told you this
to make you grieve.
>> Okay. All right. So, we are pretty far
down inferno.
And here
um in the circle of fraud, we now meet
thieves. Okay. Can I ask you a question?
I mean, like, we've we've been through
um
Inferno. We were in the circle of
violence. We met people like Axon the
Great. Uh and yeah, you can com you can
make the argument that Axon the Great is
a terrible terrible person because he
commits genocide against a lot of
people. Okay? Uh and he started wars for
no real reason except for his own glory.
um Darius the uh king of Persia offered
him many many bribes in order to not
stop to not stop fighting and his man
told him like let's just take the bribes
okay yet at the same time this thief
um he's a lot lower in inferno than a
great conqueror like the great who
killed a lot of people
why is thievery so bad.
Why
Why is thievery so evil as it warrants
such a
low status in in hell,
right?
And also like if someone's stealing,
it's often because maybe they need the
money, right?
I maybe if my child is hungry, I'm going
to go steal some something from other
people, right? Have you guys seen the
movie The Bicycle Thief? A very good
Italian movie, right?
And if you haven't, it's a really good
movie, but it's just this guy who's a
very normal guy. This is like postwar
Italy, absolutely no money, and he has
to feed his kid. So he go steals a
bicycle
and then he's you know becomes a villain
and society around him. So why is
thievery such a sin? Yes.
>> I think in like the biblical terms the
the 10 sins the greatest 10 sins you can
commit um was like the first few was
against God like using God's name in
vain and have other gods and all that.
And then the rest was like do not commit
adultery, do not lie, do not s like
steal, do not cover. Uh but all of these
the rest of the five sins were all
summarized into covering which is taking
others things like taking other's wife
is adultery you know lying to others is
taking the truth away and then there
were other things so it was all
summarized into thief or
>> so it was not a big deal right because
like the the one the one is like do not
you know um worship other idols do not
>> yeah the first few was about against God
>> and those are really bad right but like
adultery and like
>> it was like all Yeah. But the principle
behind adultery and all the other things
will all summarize into
>> right. Right. So so so in the the ten
commandments there's this hierarchy,
right?
>> Yeah. So it's so like so like stealing
is actually pretty low whereas here in
inferno it's actually pretty serious.
Right. So that that's a paradox. Yeah.
Yes.
Did did you raise your hand? Okay. All
right. Right. Do you understand there's
a paradox here? Why is killing a lot of
people not as bad as stealing from one
person? Right? And and the crime the the
sin was this guy he steals from a church
and then someone else was blamed for it.
He got away and then uh he burned in
hell, right? So he stole, someone else
was blamed and now he's burning in hell.
And the punishment is like they all get
bitten by snakes and then they die and
then they resurrect and they get bitten
by more snakes. Right?
So this is a paradox for us. Uh yes. One
reason you know in criminology
or in law and economics uh you know the
punishment is sometimes
uh measured uh or punishment uh is
calculated partially by the um the the
ability of the society to find the
crime. If a crime is very hard to find
to be observed then the the punishment
must be multiplied by the factor of this
hiddenenness. So savory uh and all this
uh fraud is more uh uh daming or more
more uh difficult more difficult to be
to be fined by open killing killing or
other uh crimes against humanity.
Although it's is a higher crime, it is
uh easy to be to be discerned by the
Zuts if there is Zuts.
>> Okay. Okay. Okay, that makes sense. But
God knows everything, right? So you
can't you can never hide your crime from
God. Uh yes. Yes. I wonder if uh I
haven't done any research on on natural
law and what Aristotle or Aristotle or
or um
Augustine would say about it, but
animals animals kill, animals rape each
other. Animals though don't put up with
animals stealing from one another. They
will like they will find a sense of
harmony. So I wonder if it goes not
against just god laws, but it goes
against natural laws as well.
>> That's a very good point. Okay. Like
animals take stealing very very
seriously. They're very they're very
protective of their own property. Yes.
Okay. Uh yes.
>> Because thievery affects uh the person
who's been thieved capacity to love and
trust uh in the future. Like maybe for
example,
>> say you're a very generous person.
Usually you leave used to leave your
house open and then you get robbed one
time. Then you're going to be very
suspicious of all your neighbors. uh
you're going to lock all your doors and
if you extrapolate this on societywide
it kills kind of kills society.
>> Yes. Does that make sense to you? Okay.
The problem with thievery is not the
stealing. The fact is that it's so no
one knows who did it. So then you you
have to like suspect everyone, right?
The problem is not that he stole and
it's not even like what he stole. The
problem is like he got away with it.
That's why thieves are worse than
everyone else because they often get
away with it. It's so secretive. It's so
shadowy. Like it no one knows who did
it, right? I guess.
>> But it didn't you just say that God
knows everything,
>> right? And God will punish you for it.
But I'm saying like what what is effect
on society?
>> Okay. Yeah. But it's not a sin against
God then. or it's not it's not a direct
sin against God. It's a sin against
society,
>> right? But for Dante, um society is what
enables us to truly
love God. Okay? So without society, we
we we couldn't actually function. Okay?
Does that make sense? So what matters
is, you know, to live a life of faith,
hope, and love. And you can only do that
in society, right? You can't do that by
yourself. You can't. So, so the society,
the social fabric is what's important.
It must hold together.
That's the logic here. Does that make
sense? Okay. All right. Uh, yes.
>> Yeah. And I also feel like while the
thieves are like deceiving the others
through like stealing, they're also kind
of like deceiving themselves. For
example, like you mentioned earlier,
what if they are poor and they're
unccapable of like um for example,
feeding their kid. I feel like with the
act of stealing, they're also like kind
of like um finding like forgiving
themselves for not reaching their full
potential because there are definitely
other ways for them to like get through
the problem.
>> Okay. Yeah. So again, the punishment is
these guys, these thieves are being
bitten by snakes, right? which kills
them. Well, that's a metaphor for what
they do in society, right? The there are
snakes. No one no one can see them. Um
they're very slippery and they just
steal from other people. But what they
don't recognize is that it's a sting on
people. It's something that um imprints
itself on people and people can never
forget it and it makes them, as you
point out, just constantly thinking
about
who stole this, right? And then what
they're going to do is they're often
going to blame someone else and it's
gonna be the wrong person, right? So
that's and and the metaphor is the snake
bite, right? A venomous treacherous
snake. Okay. Yes.
>> Yeah. I agree with your professor
because uh in in Genesis, right, the ea
there's Adam just steal the wisdom
fruit, right, from the from the tree. So
I think that is why the god feel really
angry about them try to condemn them.
That's a good point, right?
>> The snake appears in the serpent appears
in um Genesis. This cannot be a
coincidence,
>> right? It's clearly referring to first
society, one of trust between God and
Adam and Eve, and the snake convinced
them to uh disobey God and break that
trust, that bond between God. Okay,
clearly there's a reference to Genesis
here. Okay, great. Okay, let's uh Yes.
Um, I noticed like in line 108 the
resurrection of the sinners is compared
to the phoenix, but I thought the
phoenix is like a quite positive
metaphor. So I wonder why sinners are
compared to phoenix.
>> Um, so in poetry we use a lot of
metaphors and simileies. It's not really
about what's positive, what's negative.
It's really about showing you visually
what's going on, right? So, so the idea
is the visual depiction of rising from
the ashes, right? You're killed, but
then you rise again and then
the snake bites you again. And it's kind
of silly because like you already know
like you've been through this a million
times, but the snake is always able to
sneak up on you and kill you. Okay.
So, so it's a metaphor. Um, and it's and
it doesn't doesn't really care of it a
judgment. All right. Uh, let's keep on
uh reading.
Inferno Kto 25.
When he had finished with his words, the
thief raised high his fists with both
figs coughed and cried, "Take that, oh
God, I square them off for you. From
that time on those serpents were my
friends, for one of them coiled them
around his neck as if to say, "I'll have
you speak no more." Another wound about
about his arms and bound him again and
wrapped itself in front so firmly he
could not even make them budge an inch.
>> Why does he hate God so much? He curses
God, right? And he's actually the only
person we seen in front of that curses
God,
right?
Why?
>> Yes.
>> So, we said before that the effects of
thievery are so big on society, but it's
it's kind of one of those crimes that if
you're the one doing the thievery, maybe
to you it doesn't seem that bad. So, you
might feel that you're being unjustly uh
punished,
>> right? Okay. Um, why don't you think
it's a bad thing or
>> It's not that you think don't think it's
a bad thing, but
how you when you do it, you probably
don't realize how bad it is. Like we've
had the examples before about like the
Robin Hood kind of analogy of, you know,
you just take the bike or something like
that. So, you don't think it's that bad,
but then you realize in the inferno
you're in such a bad place,
>> right? So, so let's feel this, okay? He
steals a lot of things from the church
and someone else is blamed, right? When
someone else is blamed, how does he
feel?
How how would he feel?
>> Guilty. You'd feel at least bad for the
other person.
>> He's pretty ecstatic, man. Okay. Right.
Because not only has he gotten away with
it, but now he's completely innocent.
>> Do you understand?
So he's like, "The perfect crime."
And who screwed it? Who screwed it up
for him?
>> God.
>> God screwed up for him. Okay. So now
he's pissed about this. He's like, "Oh
my god, I had it all planned out. It was
a perfect crime.
Um, and I thought that I I'd get away
with it." And then God had to intervene.
Okay. So he's really angry about this.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So we'll continue after the break. Um
but an announcement um is that on
Thursday we start class earlier. We
start class at 9 o'clock. Okay? So try
to come at about 8:50. And the reason
why is we have a special guest joining
us uh Professor David Brahmich who is
starting professor of English at Yale.
He's joining us live from New Haven.
It's a real treat for for us. It'll be
live streamed to to everyone. Um and
what he's going to do is he's going to
talk about Shakespeare and then we're
going to talk about Dante. We're going
to compare and contrast Shakespeare with
Dante. Okay. So, um he's obviously one
of the world's foremost experts on
Shakespeare and we are obviously one
obviously experts on Dante already. So,
it'll be a very lively discussion. Okay.
So, something something that'll be
really fun. Uh so, please come about
8:50. We'll start at 9:00 promptly and
we'll go for for about an hour. Okay.
So, um Yep. Yep.
>> So, then are we doing like a
Three hour morning or
>> Yeah, three-hour morning. That's great.
>> Yeah. Okay. All right. All right, guys.
En enjoy your lunch. We'll come back.
Okay. After the break.
>> Okay. Um good afternoon.
>> All right. So, I want to clarify um an
issue that we had this morning, which is
why is thievery
much worse a sin than genocide?
Okay. Okay. An example is you have Axen
the Great who
for his own vanity and glory he decides
to go conquer the Persian Empire. In the
process he kills millions of people.
Okay, at least a million, possibly 10
million. Um, so a million dies and then
you have a thief who steals a holy relic
and then someone else is blamed. Okay.
And as we discussed what this does is it
destroys
trust and cohesion in the community.
Okay. But still
even if this was a large community it
would only about be a thousand people.
Okay. It would only be about a thousand
people.
So we have this strange paradox where
for Dante
uh the thief
by impacting a thousand people
it's a worse sin than accident the great
killing a million people. Okay. And how
do we reconcile this paradox? And that's
why it's important to read paradise
first because without reading paradise
it is impossible to reconcile this
paradox. There are certain aspects here
that um explain
uh the difference. First is the idea of
immortality of the soul and this
something that Beatatric will tell Dante
that the soul
um is immortal. It's eternal. It can
never die off. If your body dies off,
your soul will still be around.
Then uh what we also learn is that the
soul aspires to return to God. Okay. The
soul, its greatest desire, it greatest
happiness is to be with God. All right.
The soul returns to God.
We also learn that what allows us to
return to God is the idea of faith,
hope, and love.
Okay. All right. So once you understand
these three principles, then it's then
we can understand how this works. The
million people die. It's not a big deal.
They lose their bodies. to come back
later on. But there's a thousand people
who uh feel betrayed, who are suspicious
of each other. It is now impossible for
them to live a life of faith, hope, and
love. And in fact, it will probably
um make them more likely to sin. Okay?
So now they're moving away from God.
Okay? So um it's not the absolute
numbers that matter. It's how people
choose to live their lives that matter.
And the sin, the worst possible sin is
treachery in a way that uh forces other
people to commit treachery as well. All
right? To force you away from God. Does
this make sense, guys?
Okay. All right.
Okay. Let's let's continue.
Kanto 25
um verse let's see 10
pistoa a pisto must you last why not
decree yourself incineration since you
surpass your seed and wickedness
throughout the shadowed circles of deep
hell I saw no soul against God so re
rebel not even he who fell from thieven
walls he fled and could not say another
word and And I saw a centur full of
anger shouting, "Where is he? Where's
that bitter one?" I do not think MMA has
the number of snakes that centur carried
on his hunch until the part that takes
our human form. Upon his shoulders, and
behind his nape there lay a dragon with
its wings outstretched. It sets ablaze
all those it intercepts. My master said
that centaur there is cacas who often
made a lake of blood within a grotto
underneath Mount Aventine.
He does not ride the same road as his
brothers because he stole and most
deceitfully from the great herd nearby.
His crooked deeds his crooked deeds
ended beneath the club of Hercules who
may have given him a hundred blows but
he was not alive to feel the tenth.
While he was talking, so Cacus ran by,
and just beneath our ledge, three souls
arrived. But neither I nor my guide
noticed them until they had cried out,
"And who are you?" At this the words we
shared were interrupted, and we attended
only to those spirits. I did not
recognize them, but it happened as
chance will usually bring about that one
of them called out the other's name.
Exclaiming
where was Chianfa left behind at this so
that my guide might be alert, I raised
my finger up from chin to nose. If
reader, you're slow now to believe what
I shall tell, that is no cause for
wonder, for I who saw it hardly can
accept it. As I kept my eyes fixed upon
those sinners, a serpent with six feet
springs out against one of the three and
clutches him completely.
It gripped his belly with his middle
feet and with its four feet grappled his
two arms, and then it sank its teeth in
both it his his cheeks. It stretched its
rear feet out along his thighs and ran
its tail long between the two, then
straightened it again behind his loins.
No ivy ever gripped a tree so fast as
when that horrifying monster clasped and
intertwined the other's limbs with its.
Then, just as their substance were warm
wax, they struck they stuck together,
and they mixed their colors. So neither
seemed what had been seen before, he had
been before.
Just as when papers kindled where it
still has not caught flame in full, its
colors dark though not yet black while
white is dying off. The other two souls
stared and each one cried. A me and
yellow how you change just see you're
already neither two nor one. Then two
heads were already joined in one. When
in one face where two had been
dissolved, two intermingled shapes
appeared to us. Two arms came into being
from four lengths. The thighs and legs,
the belly, and the chest became such
limbs as never had been seen. And every
former shape was canceled there. That
perverse image seemed to share in both.
And none and so and slowly it moved on.
Just as the lizard when it darts from
hedge to hedge beneath the dog's stad's
giant lash seems if it cross one's path
a lightning flesh. So seemed a blazing
little serpent moving against the
bellies of the other two as black as and
livid as a peppercorn.
Attacking one of the it pierced right
through the part where we first take our
nourishment and then it fell before him
at full length. The one it had
transfixed stared but said nothing. In
fact, he only stood his ground and
yawned as one whom sleep or fever has
undone. The serpent stared at him, he at
the serpent, one through his wound, the
other through his mouth were smoking
violently their smoke met.
Let Lukan now be silent where he sings
of sad Zabilis and Acidius and wait to
hear what flies off from my bow. Let of
it now be silent where he tells of
Katmas Arathusa if his verse had made of
one a serpent one a fountain. I do not
envy him. He never did transmute two
natures face to face so that both forms
were ready were ready to exchange their
matter.
These were the ways they answered to
each other. The serpent split its tail
into a fork. The wounded sinner drew his
steps together. the legs and then the
thighs along with them so fastened to
each other that the juncture soon left
no sign that was discernable.
Meanwhile, the cleft tail took upon
itself the form the other gradually
lost. Its skin grew soft, the other's
skin grew hard. I saw the arms that drew
in at its armpits and also saw the
monster's two short feet grow long for
just as much as those were shortened.
The serpent's hind feet twisted up
together became the member that man
hides just as the regret put out two
hind pods from his member. And while the
smoke veils each with a new color and
now breeds hair upon the skin of one,
just as it strips the hair from off the
other, the one rose up, the other fell,
and they never turned aside their
impious eye lamps beneath which each of
them transformed his snout.
He who stood up drew his back toward the
temples, and from the excess matter
growing there came years upon the cheeks
that had been bare.
Whatever had not been pulled back, but
kept superfluous, then made his face and
nose, and thickened out his lips
appropriately.
He who was lying down thrust out his
snout, and even as the snail hauls its
horns and its horns, he drew his ear
straight back into his head. His tongue,
which had before been whole and fit for
speech, now cleaves. The other's tongue,
which had been forked, now closes up,
and the smoke stops. The soul that had
become an animal, now hissing, hurried
off along the valley. The other one
behind him speaks and spits. And then he
turned aside his new maid shoulders and
told the third soul, "I'd have buaso run
on all fours down this road as I have
done."
And so I saw the seven ballots change
and rechange. May the strangeness plead
for me if there has been some confusion
in my pen. And though my eyes were
somewhat blurred, my mind bewildered,
those three sinners did not flee so
secretly that I could not perceive Pucho
Jankato clearly. He who was the only
soul who had not been changed among the
three companions we had first met at
first, we had met at first. The other
one made you gave grieve.
>> Okay. So um these sinners
um are here because they committed
identity theft. They're imposters. They
pre pretend to be someone else. Okay?
It's like credit card credit card fraud.
And um again, this goes back to the idea
that um the lower we go, the more these
people are destroying the trust of
society and society's capacity to
function cohesively. Okay? That's why
they're being punished like this. The
punishment is fitting because uh they're
constantly being changed, right? Snakes
take over their bodies and then
dissipates their soul. Then they're
resurrected and then snakes take over
their souls again. Okay. So um but what
is unusual about this um KTO is
Dante spends a lot of time in the
description right uh Dante is usually
very economical. He spends maybe a
tursuit and then he moves on. Here we
have an entire conto talking about the
metamorphosis.
Why would he do that? And again, I don't
actually know the answer. I'm just
pointing this out, right? This is
unusual for Dante. He's usually very
sunct, very economical, very tur, and
now he's spending a lot of time going in
detail over the metamorphosis. Why would
he do that?
Any speculations?
Again, I don't know the answer. I I I
mean like I just want to speculate any
possibilities.
>> Uh maybe he want to contrast this with
heaven where the scheme is granduous and
uh extremely expensive and uh unlimited.
Here he wants to go to the reverse
to look at things uh in micro under
microscope
and uh to give you a sense of um
uh you know depth or whatever you know
give you a sense of restriction or the
opposite of of heaven.
>> Okay that that's a possibility okay to
create cont to great contrast. Yes. Any
other possibilities? Yes. I think the
depicting these u sinners
metamorphosizing is um a reflection of
them getting less and less human because
of the sin they done.
>> Yes. Right.
Any other possibilities?
Yes.
Maybe he's just trying to prove that he
can write about metaphors
as
good as all of it can.
>> Yeah, that's a very interesting idea,
right? Because there are certain poets
that Dante admires or Virgil is
definitely among the top. There's also
OIT and Lucan. Okay. And he does mention
OI and Lucan in this KTO. So, you're
right. Maybe he is trying to
uh prove that he can just be as good as
um uh ovid. Yes.
>> And also in the Bible, in the book of
Revelations, which is the last book of
the Bible, uh John wrote a lot of
visions about what he saw about angels
and you know the last day. So he maybe
he's in kind of doing that same thing as
well to show that I have divine
intervention. And I have this vision
about what's in hell, just like John had
an idea of what's in heaven.
>> Excellent. Okay. Right. So,
[clears throat] we're approaching
Lucifer, right? We're approaching the
inner core of Lucifer. And maybe what
he's trying to do is convey the sense of
fear and dread, right? He's trying to
evoke fear and dread in us because as
we're as we're reading this, we
visualize what's happening to this human
becoming a serpent. And if you think
about it, it's very hard
um not to be afraid, right? This is like
almost like a horror movie now, right?
This metamorphosis. I'm not sure if if
you seen the movie The Fly, right? This
where this guy turns into a fly. It's
pretty disgusting. It's pretty scary.
Don't don't watch it. Um Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. But but the idea of metamorphosis,
right, that we can lose our human form
and become some something else, that's
actually very very scary. Uh, and it's
hard to think of something even more
scary than that idea. And maybe he's
using that in order to evoke a sense of
fear and dread as we approach the inner
sanctums of hell. Great. These are all
great suggestions. Okay. All right. Uh,
let's keep on going.
KTO 26.
Be joyous, Florence. You're great
indeed. For overseen land you beat your
wings. Through every part of hell your
name extends. Among the thieves I found
five citizens of yours, and such that
shame has taken me. With them you can
ascend to no high honor. But if the
dreams dreamt close to dawn are true,
then little time will pass before you
feel what Praau and the others crave for
you. Were that already come, it would
not be too soon, and let it come since
it must be as I grow older, it will be
more heavy.
>> Okay. All right. So, [clears throat]
here Dante is referenced the referencing
the prophetic tradition. Okay. He is
spelling doom for Florence. He's like,
Florence, you guys should be proud
because you have more members of
Florence in hell than anyone else. Okay?
This is a great achievement and God's
going to punish you. Okay. Um,
keep on going.
Verse 10. Were that already come, it
would not be too soon, and that it come
since it must be. As I grow older, it
will be more heavy. We left that deep
and by protruding stones that served as
stairs for our descent before my guide
climbed up climbed up again and drew me
forward. And as we took our solitary
path among the ridges, jagged bursts and
rocks, our feet our feet could not make
way without our hands. It grieved me
then, and now greased me again when I
direct my mind to what I saw. And more
than usual, I curb my talent. That it
not run where virtue does not guide, so
that if my kind star or something better
has given me that gift, I not abuse it.
As many as the fireflies, the peasant
while resting on a hillside in the
season, when he who lights the world
least hides its face, just when the fly
gives way to the mosquito, sees
glimmering below down the valley there,
where perhaps he gathered grapes and
tills. So many were the flames that
glittered in the eighth abyss. I made
this out as soon as I had come to where
one sees the bottom. Even as he who he
who was avenged by bears saw as it left
Elijah's chariot its horses rearing
rising right to heaven when he could not
keep track of it except by watching one
lone flame and its ascent just like a
little cloud that climbs on high. So
through the gullet of that ditch each
flame must make its way. No flame
displays its prey, though every flame
has carried off a sinner.
I stood upon the bridge. I stood upon
the bridge and leaned straight out to
see. And if I had not gripped a rock, I
should have fallen off without a push.
My guide, who noted how intent I was,
told me. Within those fires there are
souls, each one is swathed in which in
that which scorches him. My master, I
replied, on hearing you I'm more sure.
But I'd already thought that it was so,
and I had meant to ask, who is within
the flame that comes so twinned twined
above that it would seem to rise out of
the pit itles shared with his brothers?
He answered me, "Within that flame
Ulisses and Damedes suffer. They who
went as one to rage now share one
punishment. And there together in their
flame they grieve over the horse's fraud
that caused a breach. The gate that let
Rome's noble seed escape.
There they regret the guile that makes
the dead the Demia still lament Achilles
and therefore the palladium they they
pay.
If they can speak within those sparks I
said I pray you and rep pray and master
may my prayer be worth a thousand.
Please do not forbid my waiting here
until the flame with horns approaches us
for you can see how out of my desire I
bend toward it.
>> Okay, so um the D never read Homer. So
he never read the Iliad in the Odyssey
and so his conception of Ulisses comes
from other writers.
And um Ulisses he's he's imprisoned in a
flame. Okay, he's being burned in a
flame with Diamedes. And the reason why
they're being punished is the two came
up with the idea of the Trojan horse.
This treachery, this deception that
allowed the Greeks to destroy uh the
Trojans, forcing the Trojans to go to
Rome to found the Roman uh empire. Okay.
All right. Uh let's let's keep on going.
Line 70. Line 70. and he to me, "What
you have asked is worthy of every
praise. Therefore, I favor it. I only
ask you this. Refrain from talking. Let
me address them. I have understood what
you desire of them. Since they were
Greek, perhaps they'd be disdainful of
your speech." And when my guide had
judged the flame, had reached a point
where time and place were opportune.
This was the form I heard his words
assume. You two who move as one within
the flame. If I deserved of you while I
still lived, if I deserved of you much
or a little when in the world I wrote my
noble lines, do not move on. Let one of
you retell where, having gone astray, he
found his death.
The greater horn within that ancient
flame began to sway and tremble,
murmuring just like a fire that
struggles in the wind. And then he waved
his flame tip back and forth as if it
were a tongue that tried to speak and
flung toward us a voice that answered.
When I sailed away from Cersei, who had
begiled me to stay more than a year
there near Gaata, before Anas gave that
place a name, neither my fondness for my
son, nor pity for my old father, nor the
love I old Penelope, which would have
gladdened her, was able to defeat in me
the longing I had to gain experience of
the world, and of the vices and the
worth of men. Therefore, I set out on
the open sea with but one ship and that
small company of those who never had
deserted me. I saw as far as Spain, far
as Morocco, along the both shores, I saw
Sardinia and saw the other islands that
sea bathes. And I and my companions were
already old and slow. When we approached
the narrows, where Hercules set up his
boundary stones, that men might heed and
never reach beyond. Upon my right I had
gone past Sevilla and on the left
already past Seuta.
Brothers, I said, "Oh, you who have
crossed 100,000 dangers, reached the
west to this brief waking time that
still is left unto your senses. You must
not you must not deny experience of that
which lies beyond the sun and of the
world that is unpopled. Consider well
the seed that gave you birth. You were
not made to live your lives as brutes,
but to be followers of worth and
knowledge.
I spurred my comrades with this brief
address to meet the journey with such
eagerness that I could hardly then have
held them back. And having turned our
stern toward the morning, we made wings
out of our orars in a wild flight, and
always gain upon our left hand side. At
night, I now could see the other pole in
all its stars. The star of ours had
fallen and never and never rose above
the plane of the ocean. Five times the
light beneath the moon had been
rekindled. And as many time was spent
since that hard passage phased our first
attempt, when there before us rose a
mountain, dark because of distance, and
it seemed to me the highest mountain I
had ever seen, and we were glad. But
this soon turned to sorrow, for out of
that new land a whirlwind, a whirlwind
rose and hammered at our ship against
her bow. Three times it turned her
around with all the waters. And at the
fourth it lifted up the stern so that
our prow plunged deep as pleased another
until the sea again closed over us.
>> Okay, so um uh Virgil is asking Elysius,
how did you die? Ulysius says said that
I'm a wonderer. I'm an explorer. And I
took my men and I and I rallied them and
said that we are uh we are seeking
knowledge. We are seeking uh new lands.
And this excited everyone. And we sailed
as far as a mountain. This mountain is
going to be purgatory. Okay. Uh we will
be in purgatory after we finish Inferno.
And then he sells off the um face of
this earth. Right. he uh um they just
die uh when they fall off the earth. So
this is a paradox because weren't we
told to live a life of faith, hope, and
love? And here um Ulyses, he is pursuing
what he loves and he's exploring new
lands and he's living a life of faith
that there must be new knowledge out
there for me to discover. Why would he
be in hell?
What is What did he do wrong? Uh yes. Um
first he could be just like wanting to
explore more without actually
understanding what he's seeing. And also
about the mountain being purgatory. It
could be a way of saying that if you
avoid purgatory then you finish in like
hell.
>> Interesting. Exactly. Yes. You try you
try to um run away from and you end up
in hell. Yeah, that's very interesting.
Yes. Anyone else?
No, those are great ideas. But anyone
else?
Yes.
>> Um I'm guessing like if he's trying to
know like all of the knowledge in the
world, he's trying to be like God
kind of.
>> Um okay.
Not really because
um he's just exploring, right? Okay. We
will meet someone who wants to be God
later on, but like not not here. Okay.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
Um
earlier in verse 94, neither my fondness
for my son nor pity for my old father
nor the love I owed pen penelopey do was
able to defeat in me the longing to gain
experience in this world. So um he
uh ignored and betrayed and was
treacherous towards people he should
love or loves him.
>> He he abandoned his family. Right.
Right. He has a father, Leartis. He has
a son, Tamakus. He has a wife, Penelope.
And he says, "I love my wife, but my
desire to to wonder override my love for
my own wife."
And
so why did he fail in his mission to
explore? How did he die?
He has no anchor. Right. Right. Remember
how in paradise
It is Donny's love for Beatric that
propelled him to heaven, right? Well, in
your exploration, what anchors you is
your love for family. You have to ask
yourself, why am I exploring? Like,
where am I going?
And um Ulysi didn't know, so he just
fell off the the face of the earth
because there was nothing to hold him
back. Okay. And that's why the
punishment is the flame. because the
flame of ambition, right? And he's just
trapped in his in his ambition, but
there's no body to it. There's nothing
to hold that flame back. The flame just
wanders about. Okay. So again, what D is
saying, this is like really important,
is that we as individuals, we are
ultimately anchored by our family, our
community or our society. Without these
things, we are really nothing.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay. Any
any other questions or thoughts about
this? Yes.
>> But doesn't Dante celebrate
individuality?
>> Right. But what he's saying is that
individual individual has to be anchored
to other people. You can only be an
individual
um with other people. Does that make
sense?
>> Yes.
>> Why is this worse than murder and
thiever?
>> Um yeah, that's a question. Why?
Well, thievery you are hurting those
you're you're hurting str you're hurting
strangers, right? But what Ulissa is
doing, you're hurting your own family,
right?
>> You're betraying your own kind and your
own roots.
>> Okay?
>> Right? Does that make sense? Because
because your son needs a role model,
your wife needs a husband, and your
father needs a son, and you've just
abandon them in order to pursue your own
ambition. You're ruthless. You're all
you care about is your ambition.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, good,
great question. Okay. Um, but do you do
you understand the idea? So, so do you
understand the idea that the an
individual
can only be so
um with other people? You can't be an
individual by yourself,
right? And like it's hard for for you to
appreciate, but at this time in history,
what's the worst punishment for people?
Exile, right? Does that make sense? Not
execution,
exile. Okay? And that's why Donn is so
pissed off right now because he's he's
writing this in exile from Florence and
he's like, I can't be be who I am
without Florence. Okay? You're taking
away my identity.
Does that make sense? All right. Yes.
>> Um could I uh I want to add to the
counter before to the metaphorist.
>> Sure. Sure. Sure.
>> Um the idea that
well the he the thieves get turned into
snakes. And the question is well who
else got turned into a snake? And it was
the original serpent right by God. And
the serpent was the one who basically
robbed Adam and Eve of paradise.
>> Right.
>> So basically that's like the illusion to
that.
>> Exactly. You're exactly right. Yes. Um
um and in fact Milton will use this
metamorphosis for Paradise Laws because
in Paradise Laws uh the end fate for
Satan and the devils is they all turn
into snakes. Okay. So so it's almost
like symmetry. All right. Uh thank you.
All right. Let's keep on going guys.
Okay. And I I want to commend everyone,
okay? Because now the discussion is much
more interesting. All right. So, uh this
is great. What was happening? Okay. Um
27 now.
>> 27. The flame already was erect and
silent. It had no more to say. Now it
had left us with the permission of the
gentle poet. when just behind it came
another flame that drew our eyes to
watch its tip because of the perplexing
sound that it sent forth. Even as the
Sicilian bull that first had bellowed
with the cry, and this was just of him
who shaped it with its with its
instruments would always bellow with its
victim's voice, so that although that
bull was only brass, it seemed as if it
were pierced through by pain. And so
were the helpless words that from the
first had found no path or exit from the
flame transformed into the language of
the fire.
>> Okay. Right. So um it may seem
innocuous, right? Oh, you're you're
you're trapped in a flame. Who cares?
Okay. So what Dante is doing is he's
reminding you how painful it is by
reminding you of the Sicilian bowl.
Okay. So, simil bull was this hollow
brass uh sculpture and then you were put
inside of it and you were burned inside
of it. Okay? And then you felt so much
pain that you cried and then people
outside would hear basically a a ball
moaning. All right? So, you're being
burned alive constantly. So, it's pretty
painful. Uh keep on going.
>> Line 16. But after they had found their
way up toward the tip and given it that
movement which the tongue had given them
along their passage, we heard, "Oh you
to him I turn my voice, who only now
were talking Lombard, saying, "Now you
may leave, I'll not provoke more speech.
Though I have come perhaps a little
late, may it not trouble you to stop and
speak with me. See how I stay, and I'm
burning. If you have fallen into this
blind world, but recently out of the
sweet Italian country from which I carry
all my guilt, do tell me if the
Ramanolis have peace or war. I was from
there the hills between Orbino and the
ridge where Tyber springs. I still was
bent attentive over him when my guide
nudged me lightly at the side and said,
"You speak? He is Italian." And I, who
had my answer, said already without
delay, began to speak to him. Oh soul
that is concealed below in flame. Romana
is not now and never was quite free of
war inside its tyrants hearts. But when
I left her none had broken out. Ravena
stands as it has stood for years. The
eagle of Palenta shelters it and also
covers turvia with his wings. The city
that already stood long trial and made a
bloody heap out of the French now finds
itself again beneath green paws. Both
masters of Arukio, old and new, who
dealt so badly with Montania sees used
their teeth to bore where they have
always nod. The cities on Lemona and
Satnal alert are led by the young lion
of the white lair. From summer unto
winter he shifts factions.
That city with its side bathed by the
Savio, just as it lies between the plain
and mountain, lives somewhere between
tyranny and freedom. And now I pray you,
tell me who you are. Do not be harder
than I've been with you, that in the
world your name may still endure.
After the flame, in customary fashion
had roared a while, it moved its pointed
tip aside, and that in that set free
this breath. If I thought my reply were
meant for one, whoever could return into
the world, this flame would stir no
more. And yet since none, if what I hear
is true, ever returned to life from this
abyss, then without fear facing infamy,
I answer you, I was a man of arms, then
wore the cord, believed that so ge I
made amends, and surely what I thought
would have been true had not the highest
priest, may he be damned, made me fall
back into my former sins. and how and
why I'd have you hear from me. While I
still had the form of bones and flesh my
mother gave to me, my deeds were not
those of the lion, but those of the fox.
The wilds and secret ways, I knew them
all, and so employed their arts that my
renown had reached the very boundaries
of earth. But when I saw myself come to
that part of life, when it is fitting
for all men to lower sails and gather
their ropes, what once had been my joy
was now dejection.
Repenting and confessing, I became a
frier, and poor meat would have helped.
the prince of the new Pharisees who then
was waging war so near the Lateran and
not against the Jews or Sarissens for
every enemy of his was Christian and
none of them had gone to conquer Achre
or been a traitor in the Sultan's lands
took no care for the highest office or
the holy orders that were his or for my
cord which used to make its wearers lean
but just as Constantine on Mount Sori to
cure his leprosy sought sought out
Sylvester. So this one sought me out as
his instructor to ease the fever of his
arrogance. He asked me to give counsel.
I was silent. His words had seemed to me
delirious as and then he said,
"Your heart must not mistrust. I now
absolve you in advance. Teach me to
batter Palestrino to the ground. You
surely know that I possess the power to
lock and unlock heaven. for the keys my
predecessor did not prize are two. Then
his grave arguments compelled me so my
silence seemed a worse offense than
speech. And I said, "Since you cleansed
me of the sin that I must now fall into,
Father, no long promises and very brief
fulfillments will bring a victory to
your high throne." Then Francis came as
soon as I was dead for me. But one of
the back black cherubim told him, "Don't
bear him off. Do not cheat me. He must
come down among my menials. The counsel
that he gave was fraudulent. Since then,
I've kept close track to snatch his
scalp. One can't absolve a man who's not
repented, and no one can repent and will
at once. The law of contradiction won't
allow it.
Oh miserable me, oh miserable me, for
now I started when he took hold of me
and said, "Perhaps you did not think
that I was a legician." He carried me to
Minos, and that monster twisted his tail
eight times around his hide. And then,
when he had bid it in great anger,
announced, "This one is for the thieving
fire. For which, and where you see, I
now am lost. And in it, this garb I move
in bitterness."
And with this his words were at an end.
The flame departed, sorrowing and
rifing, and tossing its sharp horn. We
moved beyond. I went together with my
guide along the ridge until the other
arch that bridges the ditch where
payment is imposed on those who since
they brought such discord bear such
loads.
>> Okay. So uh just to summarize the sinner
he gave protentant council. Okay. So he
is a military strategist and the pope
bonafice wanted to take a c a certain
city and the pope asked him for what
clever strategy can I use to take this
city and the uh sinner was like I'm
afraid of god I'm not going to tell you
and bonafice is like I speak for god I
promise you that if you help me I will
guarantee you into heaven that is my
power as pope so he says fine then
here's my advice
um grant amnesty to the people and when
they open the doors we'll just kill
everyone or or we'll we'll capture the
leaders. Okay. And that strategy does
work and um when he died he thought that
he was going to heaven and St. Francis
came down from heaven to take him to
heaven as was promised by the pope. But
then um one of the fallen angels says
you can't go because
um you gave father fraud and counsel and
so your actions determine your place in
hell.
This is a very strange story for a
variety of reasons. Let's start naming
the reasons why this is a strange story
or it doesn't really make any sense.
St. Francis came up from heaven and then
he was denied.
Okay.
Why is this a paradoxical story?
This is like really problematic story
actually.
Well, the first paradox is
um St. Francis agrees with the corrupt
Pope Bonafice, right? That's kind of
strange.
Bonafice said that if you help me, I
guarantee you uh a place in heaven. And
Bonafice
uh this isn't isn't Simony
uh but it's pretty corrupt, right? It's
pretty evil. And St. Francis up in
heaven says, "Sure. Sure. Like that's a
deal. I I'll come and get get the man."
And then the black servant had to
intervene.
This is like really problematic.
Okay. That's the first paradox.
>> Yes.
>> What's a black sherban?
>> Black sherban. A sherban is an angel,
right? So a black sherban would be a
fallen angel. Yes.
So remember when we were in paradise
there were many different orders of
angels right? So Sherbin is one of the
orders.
This is a really hard paradox right.
Francis
who is founder of the uh Franciscan
order. Those who are devoted to
uh poverty,
the one of one of the least
corruptible individuals in history.
He's helping a very corrupt pope do evil
in the world.
What's going on here?
And again, I don't know the I actually
don't know the answer. I I'm just
throwing this out there. Okay. It's
confusing me as well.
[snorts]
Something about even if St. Francis came
hear me. Hello. Something about even if
St. Francis came down and and um agrees
with Bonaf
uh that he he will try to bring this man
to heaven. Something about the law of
contradiction doesn't allow it.
Something about the nature of his
repentance.
What does it mean the contradiction
here?
Okay. What it means is yes, your heart
says I want to repent, right? But your
action says another thing. Okay. So just
because you say something, believe
something doesn't doesn't count. It's
like your action has to match these
things. Okay? So yes, you did become a
frier. You did promise yourself to a
life of God. But you also committed
treachery. You also lied to the people
inside the city, drew them out, and then
betrayed them. You also gave the pope
really bad counsel. You should have told
the pope like, "Don't do this. Don't go
against your enemies." Instead,
you um
you you helped them trick other people.
Okay? You gave father counsel. You
engage in manipulation and treachery and
deception,
right? So it doesn't matter what you
say, your actions speak for themselves.
Okay, that's the idea here. You're
condemned by your actions. Yeah, guys,
there's no answer. We're just for
possibilities. Yes.
>> Um Yeah, but I mean the Pope should have
known that this is not godlike, right?
>> And the Pope's going to burn in hell.
>> Yeah,
>> right. We already know this is going to
burn in hell.
>> Yeah,
>> right. Right. Yeah. But like almost
every pope was corrupt.
>> Well, a lot. Okay.
>> So, like almost everyone should be
there, right?
>> Yeah. There are a lot of popes burning
hell. Yes. Okay. Uh
anyone else? Yes.
>> Yeah. There's something about I mean
this one and uh and the past few kantos
there's something about manipulation
that comes to mind. It's it's it's
almost like the flip side of the
positive imagination of love by God.
This is the manipulation
of this kind of like the other side of
the coin to serve himself, right? It's
still a fundamental selfish act to to
appear
>> and that's why he's burning in hell. But
the story again, the story there are
certain paradoxes in the story. I still
don't get why Francis would come down to
honor this contract.
>> Yes.
>> Uh yeah, I would just uh uh keep asking
a question like because I know that
during back that period the black black
party to keep fighting with the white
party. So the denting which is uh uh I
think he's he's tried to uh against the
black party right but during back that
period I think the two party want to try
to compete each other who is right and
who will be uh superior so maybe in that
case that uh yeah maybe this only the
war killing people which can just allow
the uh the impair to be solidified so
>> yeah did you want to say something
something well it was a black angel that
told him that he can't bring him to
heaven. But black angels are fallen
angels, right?
>> Fallen angels don't have any power in
heaven,
>> or do they?
>> Well, no. There's like like the man
died, right? The sinner died and now
there are two angels fighting for his
body, right? St. Francis and the black
sherban. Okay. And the black sherban is
I have priority over you.
>> Why? Why does it have priority?
>> Excuse me. Why does it why does a fallen
angel have more priority than
>> Yeah, that's a paradox, right?
I'm saying like there are a lot of
paradoxes in the story. One paradox is
yes, uh why did Francis agree to help
him? And two, how did the black sherpian
have more power than St. Francis?
Right. These are paradoxes.
All right. Okay. Let's try to unpack
what's going on. Okay. Point one is that
[clears throat]
the pope bonafice says that at the keys
to heaven.
Okay. So what this is saying is that as
pope he is the rep representative of god
on earth. Okay. So he does have a
certain power and that's why the sinner
agrees to such duplicity because he's
guaranteed right. There's a contract at
at at play. Right. Okay.
And then because of this contract uh St.
Francis has to come and honor this
contract otherwise you're you're
avoiding the authority of the church of
the Catholic Church on earth. Okay, does
that make sense?
But this is saying that there are these
laws that are above the contract in the
Catholic Church.
Okay.
And at this point in history to hear
these ideas would be revolutionary,
right? Because at this time in history,
everyone did believe the pope was the
representative of God on earth. And and
Catholics still do today. And the pope
literally has a power to grant you
access to heaven. Okay? So that's what I
think is going is going on, but I could
be wrong. Okay? Right. This is all just
speculation. Any other thoughts or
comments about about this?
Just following up on what you just said,
I think justice trumps the Catholic
Church and that authority.
>> Yeah. And this is revolutionary at this
time at this point in history is
history, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Okay.
>> This alludes to the universality of
truth like there there is something
governing even
you know the angels close to God.
>> That's right. Okay. Yes, there is a
cosmic order. Okay. All right. Let's
keep on going.
KTO 28.
Who even with untrabled words and at
many attempts at telling ever could
recount in full the blood and wounds
that I now saw? Each tongue that tried
would certainly fall short because the
shallowess of both our speech and
intellect cannot contain so much. Were
you to reassemble all the men who once
within a puliest fateful land had
mourned their blood shed at the Trojan's
hands as well as those who fell in the
long war where massive mounds of rings
were battle spoils even as Libby writes
who does not and those who felt the
thrust of painful blows when they fought
hard against Robert Biscar with all the
rest whose bones are still piled up at
Cheperano. Ichipoleon was a traitor
there and two at Taliao where oldardo
conquered without weapons and then where
one to show his limb pierced through and
one his limb hacked off that would not
match the hideousness of the ninth
abyss. No barrerow even though it's lost
a hoop or hand and peace ever gapes as
one whom I saw ripped right from his
chin to where we fart. His bowels hung
between his legs once saw his vitals and
the miserable sack that makes of what we
swallow swallow excrement.
While I was all intent on watching him,
he looked at me and with his hands he
spread his chest and said, "See how I
split myself. See now how maimed
Mohammed is. And he who walks and weeps
before me is Ali, whose face is opened
wide from chin to forlock. and all the
others here whom you can see where when
alive the sers of dissension and scandal
and for this they now are split.
>> Okay. So this in this uh part of hell uh
these are people who've caused civil
discord war between families. Okay. And
the first two people people we see being
punished are Muhammad and Ali. And this
of course would be confusing to a lot of
people especially Muslims. Okay. So what
how understands this is that he thinks
um that Islam is just splitting off from
Christianity. Right? You believe you all
read the Bible, you believe in the same
God. And so this is basically just a
division
uh of of two religions. Okay? So at this
time in history uh Catholics believe
that Muhammad was just leading leading a
a a heresy. Okay. So and then Ali is
Muhammad's grandson. He caused a
division among the Islamic faith between
the Shia Muslims and the Sunni Muslims.
Okay. The Shia Muslims believe that only
an ances sorry only a descendant of
Muhammad can be khalif be the supreme
leader. And the Sunnis believed no
that's not necessarily the case. Okay.
And that caused a massive shism which
continues to to today. Okay. [snorts] Um
and so for creating this um discord
their bodies are constantly ripped in
half and split all the time. Okay. All
right. Uh let's keep on going.
Line 37. Behind us here, a devil decks
us out so cruy, replacing everyone of
this throng underneath the sword edge
when we've made our way around the road
of pain. Because our wounds have closed
again before we have returned to meet
his blade once more. But who are you who
dotle on this ridge perhaps to slow your
going to the verdict that was pronounced
on yourself? Accusations.
Death has not reached him yet, my master
answered. Nor is it guilt that summons
him to torment, but that he may gain
full experience. I, who am dead, must
guide him here below, to circle after
circle throughout hell. This is as true
as that I speak to you. More than a
hundred, when they heard him, stopped
within the ditch, and turned to look at
me, forgetful of their torture,
wondering. Then you who will perhaps
soon see the sun, tell Fra doino to
provide himself with food, if he has no
desire to join me here quickly, lest
when snow besiees him, it bring the
novar re the victory that otherwise they
would not find too easy. When he had
raised his heel as if to go, Muhammad
said these words to me, and then he said
it on the ground, and off he went.
Another sinner, with his throat slit
through, and with his nose hacked off up
to his eyebrows, and no more than a
single year remaining, had with the
other stayed with his steps in wonder,
he was the first before the rest to open
his windpipe, on the outside all blood
read, and said, "Oh, you whom guilt does
not condemn, and whom, unless too close
resemblance cheats me, I've seen above
upon Italian soil, remember peer mach
medachina, if you ever again the gentle
plain that from Verelli slopes to Marco.
And let the two best men of Fano know, I
mean both Messer Guido and Angelo, that
if the foresight we have here is not
vain, they'll be cast out of their ship
and drowned, weighed down with stones
near Catholica because of a foul
tyrant's treachery.
Between the isisles of Cypress and
Minorca, Neptune has never seen so cruel
a crime committed by the pirates or the
Argus. That traitor who sees only with
one eye and rules the land which one
who's here with me would wish his sight
had never seen will call Guido and
Angelo to a parlay, and then will so
arrange it that they'll need no vow or
prayer to Fakara's wind. And I to him,
if you would have me carry some news of
you above, then tell and show me who so
detests the sight of remining. And then
he set his hand upon the jaw of a
companion opening his mouth and
shouting. This is he, and he speaks not.
A man cast out. He quenched the doubt in
Caesar, insisting that the one who
prepared can only suffer harm if he
delays.
Oh, how dismayed and pain he seemed to
me, his tongue slit in his gullet. Curio
who once was so a dashes in his talk and
one who walked with both his hands
hacked off while lifting off his stumps
through the dark air so that his face
was hideous with blood cried out you
will remember Mosca too who said alas
what's done is at an end which was the
seed of evil for the Tuscans
I added and brought death to your own
kinsmen then having heard me speak grief
heaped on grief he went his way as one
gone mad with sadness. But I stayed
there to watch their company and saw a
thing that I should be afraid to tell
with no more proof than my own self.
Except that I am reured by conscience
that good companion heartening a man
beneath the breastplace of its purity. I
surely saw and it still seems I see a
trunk without a head that walked just
like the others in that melancholy herd.
It carried by the hair its severed head
which swayed within its hand just like a
lantern. And that head looked at us and
said, "Ah, me." Out of itself it made
itself a lamb. And they were two and one
and one and two. How that can be, he
knows who so decrees. When it was just
below the bridge, it lifted its arm
together with its head so that its word
might be more near us. Words that said,
"Now you can see atrocious punishment.
You who still breathing go to view the
dead. See if there's any pain as great
as this. And so that I you may carry
news of me. Know that I'm Bertrand
Deborore, the one who gave bad counsel
to the fledgling king. I made the son
and father enemies and and Kitaphell
with his malicious urgings to not do
worse with Abselum and David. Because I
severed those so joined I carry alas my
brain decevered from its source which is
within my trunk and thus in me one sees
the law of counter penalty. Okay. So we
are we are these sinners committed um
they sold discord and this discord
became permanent right. So we talked
about Muhammad and Ali. Then there's
courio who um um sold discord between
Caesar and Pompei who were previously
good friends. This is this uh led to a
massive civil war in uh in Rome which
will end only with the rise of the Roman
Empire. You also have betray the born
and he's lost his head because he caught
discord. He caused discord or civil war
between a father king and a son the
prince. Okay. Um just for fun
um who you put into this circle
like today like from from from history
or from today or just from your
imagination. Who would you put into this
circle? A sort of discord
just for fun. Yes.
>> Hitler.
>> Excuse me.
>> No,
that's that's not what he did. Yes.
Okay. Because like I asked people like
who who belongs in hell? Your first
first thought is Hitler, right? But like
let's think about the punishment. Okay.
So of discord.
Uh yes. uh representative of Democrats
and Republicans and like far right far
left.
>> But but but can you give me an example
>> like Trump for Republicans and like Kim
Harris?
>> Maybe Donald Trump, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Maybe Donald Trump because Donald
Trump has led to the polarization of
American society,
right? It's either you are for him or
against him. Yes. So So good good good
idea. Yes.
>> Uh yes. along that line. I was gonna say
JD Vance.
>> Why? Why does JD Vance?
>> Because he also sews conflict.
>> But then every politician s conflict
then, right? Um yeah, but but but yeah,
Trump is a good suggestion. Anyone else?
It doesn't have to be a real real
person. It could also be a fictional
character, a movie character. Okay. Or
just someone from your life that you
really really don't like. Okay. Yes.
>> Social media in general and the makers
of it. So Mark Zuckerberg,
right?
Is that a possibility?
>> Because you schism, it doesn't have to
be like turning one into two. It can be
turning one into multiple scatter.
>> Well, no. No. The idea of like the
social media algorith algorithms is that
they're trying to provoke anger because
with anger, you're much more engaged.
You're much more likely to use uh social
media, right? So someone like Mark
Zuckerberg is a source of discord and
that's a maj major concern about social
media right before you had the evening
news and evening news was a place to
build consensus to build community with
social media you just go in your live in
your own bubble and then you start
arguing with other people and then it's
no longer about finding consensus it's
just about like beating the other guy
right so Mark Zuckerberg
arguably is a source of discord along
with Donald Trump yeah these are two
good good suggestions Anyone else?
[snorts]
>> Yes.
>> Maybe not a good one, but uh Greta
Thumbberg.
>> Okay. Why?
>> Like she she creates discord between
people who seek like money without like
looking at the earth like environmental.
So she creates division between people
who believe in environment and people
who just make money and billionaires.
>> Um right. Okay. But is she is she the
root of this conflict? Is she the cause
of this conflict?
Uh yes.
Yeah. Just media in general I guess is
like the biggest polarizing factor like
any media form like newspapers
u movies maybe even
>> right media. Sure.
>> Just media.
>> Right. I'm looking for a name guys.
Okay. You you can't put media into hell.
You have to put a person in hell. Yes.
Make maybe Nick Fuentes for his accusing
Jewish people in Zionist.
>> Yeah, I I I I think that's a good choice
as well. Nick Fuentes. Yes. Right. Yes.
Right.
>> Just following his idea. I was going to
say Charlie Kirk.
>> Some people believe that. Yes. Right.
Depends on your politics, but some
people do do believe that. Yes. Um
>> schism though. like this idea of schism.
What why what are we schisming like
we're separating?
>> Yeah, that's a good point.
>> What are we separating
>> Yes.
>> from?
>> Right. So So the best choice would be
Donald Trump because he caused a schism
in the Rep Republican party, right?
Between conservative Republicans and
MAGA, right? That's that's a pretty good
>> but but but according to Dante, this is
schisming from God, right? And I mean
there's
>> not necessarily
>> not necessarily.
>> Not necessarily. No.
>> Right. because Caesar and Pompei didn't
believe in God. Right.
Okay. All right. So, this is this is
just an exercise. Okay. It's like like
like it's not political commentary. Yes.
All right. Yes. All right. Let's keep on
going.
KTO 29.
So many souls and such outlandish one.
outlandish wounds had made my eyes
inebriate. They longed to stay and weep.
But Virgil said to me, "Why are you
staring so insistently? Why does your
vision linger there below among the lost
and mutilated shadows? You did not do so
at the other moes. If you would count
them all, consider. 22 miles make up the
circuit of the valley. The moon already
is beneath our feet. The time allotted
to us now is short, and there's more to
see than you see here." Had you, I
answered him without a pause, been able
to consider why I looked, you might have
granted me a longer stay. Meanwhile, my
guide had moved ahead. I went behind
him, answering as I walked on, and
adding in that hollow upon which just
now I kept my eyes intent, I think, a
spirit born of my own blood laments the
guilt which down below costs one so
much. At this my master said, don't let
your thoughts about him interrupt you
from here on. attend to other things.
Let him stay there. For I saw him below
the little bridge, his finger pointing
at you, threatening, and heard him
called by name, Jerry Debello."
But at that moment you were occupied
with him, who once was Lord of Honapor.
You did not notice Jerry. He moved off.
My guide, it was his death by violence,
for which he still is not avenged, I
said, by anyone who shares his shame
that made him so distable now. And I
suppose, for this he left without a word
to me. and this has made me pity him the
more. And so we talked until we found
the first point of the ridge that if
there were more light would show the
other valley to the bottom. When we had
climbed above the final cloister of
Malibul, so that its lay brothers were
able to appear before our eyes, I felt
the force of strange laments like arrows
whose shafts are barbed with pity. And
at this I had to place my hands across
my ears. Just like the sufferings that
all the sake of Valdicana's hospitals,
Mormas, Sardinas from July until
September would muster if assembled in
one ditch, so was it here. And such a
stench rose up as usually comes from
festering limbs. And keeping always to
the left, we climbed down to the final
bank of the long ridge. and then my
sight could see more vividly into the
bottom where unuring justice the
minister of the high lord punishes the
falsifiers she had registered. I do not
think that there was greater grief in
seeing all Aena's people sick than when
the air was so infected that all animals
down to the little worm collapsed and
afterward as poets hold to be the
certain truth those ancient peoples
received their health again through seed
of ants. Then I felt when I saw in that
dark valley the spirits languishing in
scattered heaps. Some lay upon their
bellies, some upon the shoulders of
another spirit. Some crawled on all
fours along that squalid road. We
journeyed step by step without a word,
watching and listening to those six
souls who had not strength enough to
lift themselves.
I saw two sitting propped against each
other as panis propped on pan to heat
them up. Heat them up. and each from
head to foot spotted with scabs. And I
have never seen a stable boy whose
master waits for him, or one who stays
awake reluctantly so by a horse with
currical
themselves with clawing nails, their
itching had such force and fury, and
there was no other help. And so that
nails kept scraping off the scabs just
as a knife scrapes off the scales of
carp or of another fish with scales more
large.
Oh you who use your nails to strip
yourself, my guide began, my guide began
to say to one of them, and sometimes
have to turn them into pincers. Tell us
if there are some Italians among the
sinners in this moat. So may your nails
hold out eternal at their work. We too
who you see so disfigured here. We're
Italians, one said in tears. But who are
you who have inquired of us? My guide
replied, "From circle down to circle,
together with this living man, I'm one
who descends. I mean to show him how."
At this their mutual support broke off,
and quivering, each spirit turned toward
me with other who by chance had heard
his words. Then my good master drew more
close to me, saying, "Now tell them what
is it what it is you want." and I began
to speak just as he wished,
so that your memory may never fade
within the first world from the minds of
men, but still live on and under many
sons. Do tell me who you are and from
what city, and do not let your vile and
filthy torment make you afraid to let me
know your names."
One answered me, "My city was a redso,
and Albero, a sienna, had me burned, but
what I died for does not bring him here,
bring me here. It's true that I had told
him justestingly. I'd know enough to fly
through air, and he with curiosity but
little sense wished me to show that art
to him, and just because I had not made
him dalis, had one who held him as a son
burn me. But Minos, who cannot mistake,
condemned my spirit to the final pouch
of 10, for alchemy I practice in the
world.
And then I asked the poet, "Was there
ever so vain a people as the Cianese,
even the French can't match such
vanity?" At this the other leper who had
heard me replied to what I said, "Except
for Streka, for he knew how to spend
most frugally, and Nicolo, the first to
make men see that cloves can serve as
luxury. Such seed and gardens where its
suits can take fast root, and two,
Katcha Dashano's company. With him he
squandered vineyards and tilled fields,
while Abalato showed such subtlety. But
but if you want to know who joins you so
against the Sianes, look hard at me.
That way my face can also answer lightly
and see that I'm the shade of that
capoio whose alchemy could counterfeit
fine metals. And you, if I correctly
take your measure, recall how at I was
at aping nature.
>> Okay. All right. So this is really
interesting because we've reached the
lowest
um area of hell and this area is
reserved for those who engage in
alchemy. Okay. Now alchemy is something
that that's very common back at this
time. Alchemy is basically trying to
find uh trying to turn lead into gold.
It's trying to find the elixir of youth
um or immortality. Okay.
So, you're trying to
do chemistry basically. Why would this
be the worst sin in the circle of fraud?
What's the issue with this? We we know
why thievery is an issue.
We we we know why uh identity theft is
an issue.
We
I understand all this, but why why would
alchemy be an issue? In fact, it's the
worst thing you can you can do in in
fraud. Yes. Because it gives people
false hope and say like people waste
their life pursuing something that is
not real,
>> right? But then you can argue that
heresy is the same thing, right? Uh
yeah. Yes. Yes.
>> So is it because of like these
alchemists, they actually feed some of
like what you want? For example, they
feed your greed, they feed like this uh
your your want of for example love or
immortality,
>> right? But but all people who commit
fraud do that, right? Why are they the
worst of all these fraudsters? Did Did
you um
>> It's like you're you're trying to change
the whole fabric fabric of the world.
>> Yes.
>> You're trying to bend everything for
your wants and desires.
>> Yes. You're trying to change the loss of
God. Okay. It's not that you're not
going to succeed, but the fact that
you're trying, the fact that people are
helping you try, that's a problem.
Okay. is a bad example.
Okay. So, before we we're discussing
society, right? The law of society and
how people warp society with fraud. But
now with alchemy, you're trying to warp
nature with fraud. Okay. And that's even
worse.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Right. Uh yes,
>> this is a bit of a weird question, but I
[clears throat] saw some thought of some
parallels. But would you say like for
example today the striving and working
towards AI is kind of like old alchemy
because we're trying to fabric of AI is
alchemy guys.
>> Yes, you're exactly right. Okay. Uh yes.
>> How about nuc nuclear energy? Nuclear.
>> It is it is alchemy. It is alchemy.
>> It is it is complete complete alchemy.
Yes, that's right. Yes.
>> How about moon landing? It's also
considered as alchemy. What do you
think? Excuse me.
>> Mool landing. Moon landing.
>> Moon landing.
>> Yes.
>> Um, it's not alchemy, but you're also
going against the laws of nature, right?
It's like Ulisses falling off the the
edge of the earth, right? It's like, why
are you on the moon, guys? Like, like,
why?
There are poor people back here. Okay,
there's lots of problems here. Solve the
problems first before you go to the
moon. Okay. So, it's not alchemy, but
it's still problematic. Okay. But AI is
100% alchemy. Nuclear energy is uh also
problematic. Okay. It's also alchemy.
Okay.
Uh yes.
>> But but what if the uh just like AI who
can give the people job, give people
hope or leave the love? Is this still
the economy?
>> It's a huge problem. Yes. Right. Yes.
Did you?
>> A few decades ago, they would have said
the internet is alchemy. But the
internet has brought you know education
like this YouTube live stream to
millions of people and it it's also
improved jobs. So is that like would you
also say the internet is alchemy?
>> The internet is not alchemy
>> but then AI is alchemy.
>> Right. Right. Okay. So so so so can you
try to explain the difference between AI
and and the internet? [snorts]
Like the the internet facilitates
normal worldly ideas to spread but AI is
from nothing creating.
>> What does AI stand for?
>> Artificial.
>> That's alchemy guys. Creating
intelligence artificially, right?
Turning lead into gold. Artificial
intelligence. Yes. I I guess I guess I
mean um uh just taking the the the the
thesis of this whole course is to assume
that this is divinity, right? I guess
one of the things that I can see here is
a warning
about manipulating nature, manipulating
reality, the nature of reality itself is
that the risks that these things come
with are unimaginable. It is it is
potentially the worst.
>> Yeah. So the problem with our world
today is like we don't think there are
moral laws at work right we are in a
post-truth world right we are beyond god
we can be our own god uh yes
>> maybe similar to artificial intelligence
is artificial insemination or uh genetic
manipulation in order to create the
perfect
>> that is correct yes
>> perfect offspring and numerous offspring
>> yes is you're absolutely Correct. It is
alchemy. That is alchemy. Uh yes. Um did
Yes. Did you have a
>> Yeah. It's like uh I feel curious like
how could we like why we regard AI as
argument but obviously he has mentioned
a part of but uh but but for me I feel a
little bit confused because I thought
like based on a algorithm it's I know
it's like artificial it's intelligence
but still it's currently those models
doesn't have their own power to create
it idea that never have occurred before.
So like for me AI is still a tool that
is more objectively like help you to
search out the information that has
already been exist. So from my point of
view AI may not like obey the law of God
because it's actually doesn't create
something. It's just like trying to sort
out the information for you.
>> Right. Right. I understand this. But for
Donnie the concern is the intent. It is
the intent. If you talk to people who
work in AI they're like we're trying to
create God. Okay,
>> you understand? So, alchemy, right?
Trying to turn lead into gold. It
doesn't work. We know it doesn't work.
There'll never be immortality. But what
are all these Silicon Valley building
spending their money on? Immortality,
right? It's not that you'll succeed, but
it's like you you intend to do this.
Okay.
Right.
That's the issue.
All right. Uh yes. So if uh nuclear
power is alchemy is for example fossil
fuels or um like renewable energies also
alchemy.
Um okay so nuclear energy we can debate
about. Okay. Um
but yeah, I would say nuclear energy is
alchemy because
um and I think the crucial distinction
is that with nuclear energy
you're you're entering into territory
that is the very fundamental na fabric
of nature of the universe, right? And
you don't actually know the consequences
of your actions, right? Look, there
there are people who believe like the
entire point of the nuclear bomb is to
open portals
to welcome summon demons into our world.
There are literally people who believe
that, right? That's alchemy.
Okay. So, the point isn't as nuclear
weapon weapons are not meant to be a
weapon. They're meant to be a portal to
summon interdimensional aliens or demons
into our world. Okay. Uh yeah. So, so
it's of intent. Yes.
Yeah, with this intention then I wonder
alchemy is turning lead to gold which is
which is impossible by the laws of
chemistry and God.
The splitting of the atom is possible.
We've done it. So I wonder if this
intention to a thing that cannot happen
is alchemy where a thing that can happen
is no different than me taking medicine
for a sickness. God put that sickness in
my body. God gave me the ability to cure
the sickness. The intention is there on
both of them. One one is within the
realm of the fabric of the universe. one
is clearly not
>> right. Okay. So, that's a really
interesting comment. Okay. And so, how
would Donnie respond to this? Well, you
have the intention, but you're not going
to succeed, so who cares? How would
Donnie respond to that?
You would say,
"If there's a will, there's a way." You
understand? So, you we think we cannot
turn lead into gold, but we actually
have succeeded in doing so because now
we have the idea of money, right?
What is money? Money is alchemy. Because
what I've done is I've taken a piece of
paper, right? Any piece of paper, and
I've turned it into gold, right? Is
How's that different from alchemy?
I can now use this money to go buy a
house or buy a car. Yes.
>> I guess the the difference would be
classification. You you're turn you
turned that paper into wealth, but you
did not turn it into gold. So,
>> but but but but what is gold?
>> So, gold is wealth, right? They're both
wealth. They're both types of wealth,
but you did not turn it into the
physical components of
>> Well, I can tell you I can use money to
buy gold.
>> Yeah. You So, you turned them both into
wealth. They both have value. You turn
them into purchasing power, but you
didn't turn it is into the physical
components of gold.
>> No, no, no. But what I'm saying is like
lead into gold, right? If I add an
intermediary step, which is like to
print money, then I solve the problem,
right?
I can use money to buy gold and then I
can sell lead to get money.
Okay.
So, how's that different? So, so, so I'm
not saying, you know, we succeed at turn
into gold. I'm saying like for Dante,
the concern is where there's a will,
there's a way. We can never ever
underestimate the human imagination.
That's the animating force of the
universe, right? So, we set our intent
on something and this intent is
malicious, then that's a sin.
Yes.
>> Yeah. I also agree with the fact that if
you have a will to distort the order
that God has set up to be, then that's
the ultimate sin. Just like the Tower of
Babel, where there's a whale, there's a
way. So, people are building the tower
of Babel to reach heaven and be like, we
can reach God, we can let God.
Basically, it's like the first landing
of the moon. like people trying the
impossible, you know, going into outer
space and God was like, "Oh, no, you
guys are not going to do that. I'm going
to give you languages so you guys are
messed up, so you can't do that." But
that the sub um messages is that if
people so well continue, they probably
can because there's a will, you know,
there's a way. And so that's why God had
to send us different languages to stop,
you know, uh people working towards that
goal. So I think it's the same scene
that's repeated here. It's like if
there's a way, a whale, there's a way.
So if there's a will to replace God,
right, and distort his order that he has
established in the natural laws, you
know, then it's abomination,
>> right? Okay. Uh yes,
>> I think there is a
kind of philosophical but also German
concept. It's called anten, right? And
and is you de art, you know, denature to
turn something into another nature to to
basically to betray your nature.
And at E N T A R A T N. Yeah.
>> And naturalize.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So basically to uh to um to deprive the
the the
Yeah. Okay, that's you you play better.
>> Well, what no but why is it why is it a
German
>> an art basically is uh is chemistry
because it's basically
uh try to deprive the uh the human being
or the you know godly kingdom of its uh
original purpose.
>> Why is it just a German thing? You know
alchemy is a purpose you know the the
intent is to to you know take over the
kingdom of god you know the whatever the
humanity and to replace his world with
your own personal you know will and
that's I think is uh goes beyond the the
nature of you know the rule rules of
nature and then that's a you know crime
against humanity
>> right and we can also uh appreciate that
um these alchemists are sinful Because
even though they're not successful, they
still try they still make people believe
that it's possible to change the rules
of nature, which leads to hubish, which
leads to a lot of like really bad
behavior. Okay. All right. Okay. So,
does that make sense, guys? All right.
Let's let's continue. Uh but thank you
so much for that. Okay. It's a really
interesting idea and we'll come back to
it later on because we live in an age of
AI and uh what I want to do as we move
on is try to use uh Dante to better
understand the most pressing issues of
our time including AI. Okay. All right.
So this is infernal 30.
KTO 30. When Juno was inscented with
Semile and thus against the Thean family
had shown her fury time and time again.
Then Atheus was driven so insane that
seeing both his wife and their two sons
as she bore one upon each arm, he cried,
"Let's spread the nets to take the
lioness together with her cubs along the
path." And he stretched out his talent,
his talents, Pinilas, and snatched the
son who bore the name Learchus, whirled
him around, and dashed him on a rock.
She with her other burden drowned
herself. And after fortune turned
against the pride of Troy, who had dared
also that the king together with his
kingdom was destroyed. Then Hecuba was
wretched, sad, a captive, and after she
had seen Polyena dead, and it mis in
misery had recognized her polyodoris
lying on the shore, she barked out of
her senses like a dog. Her agony had so
deformed her mind. But neither fury,
thieven, and Trojan ever was seen to be
so cruel against another. In rending
beasts, and even human limbs, as were
two shades I saw, both pale naked, who
biting ran berserk in just the way a hog
does when it slits loose from its thigh.
The one came at Capo uh Capoio and sank
his tusks into his neck so that by
dragging he made the hard ground scrape
against his belly. And he who stayed
behind the aratini trembled and said
that phantoms Johnny sneaky and he does
raging rending others so he goes raging
rending others so and oh I said to him
so may the other not sink its teeth in
you. Please tell me who it is before it
hurries off from here. And he to me that
is the ancient soul of the indecent
mirror. She who loved her father passed
the limits of just love. He ca she came
to sin with him by falsely taking
another shape upon herself just as the
other phantom who goes there had done
that he might gain the lady of the herd
when he disguised himself as Boso Donati
making a will as if most properly. And
when the pair of raging ones had passed,
those two on whom my eyes were fixed, I
turned around to see the rest of the
illorn. I saw one who had been fashioned
like a loot, if he had only had his
groin cut off from that part of his
body, where it forks. The heavy dropsy
which so deport disproportions the limbs
with unassimilated humors, that there's
no match between the face and belly, had
made him part his lips like a consump a
consumptive. who will because of thirst
let one lip drop down to his chin and
lift the other up.
Oh, you exempt from every punishment in
this grim world, and I do not know why,
he said to us. Look now, and pay
attention to this, the misery of Master
Adam alive. I had enough of all I
wanted. Alas, I now long for one drop of
water. The rivulletes that fall into the
Arno, down from the green hills of the
canentino, with channels cool and moist,
are constantly before me. I'm racked by
memory. The image of their flow parches
me more than the disease that robs my
face of flesh flesh. The rigid justice
that would torment me uses as most
appropriate the place where I had sinned
to draw swift size from me. There's
Romina. There I counterfeited the
currency that bears the Baptist seal.
For this I left my body burned above.
But could I see the miserable souls of
Guido, Allesandro, or them or their
brother? I'd not give up the sight for
Fonty Bra, and one of them is in this
moat already. If what the angry shades
report is true, what use is that to me
whose limbs are tied? Were I so light
that in a hundred years I could advance
an inch, I should already be well upon
the road to search for him among the
mutilated ones. Although the circuit
measures some 11 miles and is at least a
half mile across, because of them I'm in
this family, it was those three who had
incited me to coin the Florence with
three carrot straws. And I to him, where
are those two poor sinners who give off
smoke like wet hands in the winter and
lie so close to you upon the right? I
found them here, he answered. When I
rained down to this rocky slope, they've
not stirred sins and will not move. I
think eternally one is the lying woman
who blamed Joseph, the other lying son,
Greek from joy, because of raging fever
they wreak so. And one of them who
seemed to take offense perhaps of being
named so squalidly, struck with his fist
at Adam's rigid belly. It sounded as if
it had been a drum, and Master Adam
struck him in the face, using his arm,
which did not seem less hard, saying to
him, "Although I cannot move my limbs
because they're too heavy, I still have
an arm that's free to serve that need."
And he replied, "But when you went to
burning, your arm was not as quick as it
was now. Though when you coined, it was
as quick and more." To which the drop
seed one, "Here you speak true, but you
were not so true a witness there. when
you were asked to tell the truth at
Troy. If I spoke false, you falsified
the coin, said Sinon. I'm here for just
one crime, but you've committed more
than any demon. Do not forget the horse,
you perjurer, replied the one who had
the bloated belly. May you be plagued
because the whole world knows this. The
Greek, and you be plagued by thirst that
cracks your tongue and putrid water that
has made your belly such a hedge before
your eyes. And then the coiner. So as
usual, your mouth because of racking
fever gapes. For if I thirst and if my
humorous bloats me, you have both
dryness and a head that aches. Few words
would be sufficient invitation to have
you lick the mirror of narcissists. I
was intent on listening to them when
this was what my master said. If you
insist on looking more, I'll quarrel
with you. And when I heard him speak so
angrily, I turn around to him with shame
so great that it still stirs within my
memory. Even as one who dreams that he
is harmed and dreaming, wishes he were
dreaming, thus desiring that which is as
if it were not. So I became within my
speechlessness, I wanted to excuse
myself, and did excuse myself, although
I knew it not.
Less shame would wash away a greater
fault than was your fault, my master
said to me. Therefore, release yourself
from all remorse and see that I'm always
at your side. Should it so happen once
again that fortune brings you where men
would quarrel in this fashion. To want
to hear such bickering is base.
>> Okay. All right. So, this is a very
complicated conto. Okay. There are lots
of individuals and there's a lot going
on. Okay. So in this last area of the
circle of fraud, there are lots of
people who are condemned here. Okay,
they are of course the alchemists.
Then you have um impostors,
people who steal people's identity. Then
you have counterfeits.
And
so first of all, what do we have?
Actually, you know what, Carol, could
you could you do me a favor and Google
this? Like, um, who's actually in uh,
KTO 30? So, so, so, so I want to make
sure I'm correct here, okay? I I I want
to make sure because this is a very
confusing KTO and there are lots of
different individuals. Okay, so
let's see who they are.
Okay.
Okay, so these are the falsifiers. Yes,
you have Master Adam who's a
counterfeitter. You have a spy
who's a false witness. You have Jenna
Siti who is a impostor. And you have
um Mea Marha. Okay. And so the two
people who are having an argument are
Son and Master Adam, right? Master Adam
is a counterfeitter and Son is a Greek
spy who convinced the Trojans to take in
the Trojan horse. They're having an
argument about who is worse.
Um Jenny Seti,
he
is a impostor
who
uh disguised himself as a dead person.
Okay. So, first of all, what is the
connection among all these people, the
falsifiers?
It's a very confusing section. You have
a counterfeitter, you have a spy, you
have an impostor, you have
Myra who uh disguised herself to commit
incest for her own father. Oh, what's
going on here?
Maybe this is a just a garbage heap of
hell, right? Like you don't belong in
any other category, so you just stumped
here. But that's not Dante, right? We we
already said that Dante there's a lot of
intentionality, there's a lot of
creativity, there's a lot of
imagination. So what is he doing here?
All right. So let's look at certain
things that happens. Okay. So the
alchemist
uh who suffers who suff who suffers from
leprosy. Okay. Their their punishment is
leprosy.
Uh Diani the impostor he sinks his teeth
into
the leper.
What does this signify? Do you think?
And again it's all speculation guys. We
don't know. Okay.
We we don't actually know what the
allegor allegorical meaning is. We're
just speculating here. Okay. But but
there's this violent scene where the
impostor Giani, he sings his teeth into
the alchemist and tries to eat him.
[snorts]
>> Yes. Yes. So impostor basically is a
person who tried to steal somebody
else's identity and uh so this uh this u
you know a appropriate uh punishment or
educational course for them is to to to
let them sink their uh uh you know to uh
consume the identity of a of a very uh
evil person so that they will uh it will
be satiated.
>> Okay. Yeah. So um the thing though is
that the alchemist is a leopard. Okay.
And at this time in history who who does
everyone want to avoid lepers. Okay. So
uh the punishment for this impostor is
uh he's forced to just randomly eat
people including those who are lepers.
Okay. Okay. So that makes sense.
Why would Master Adam, who's a
counterfeitter, why would he argue with
Sina about who's worse?
And this is actually the first time in
Divine Comedy, we see an argument
between two souls, right? These two
sinners. And the argument like who's
worse,
right? Well, I mean, like technically
they're all they're all equally bad,
right? Because they're in the same area
of hell.
So what what are they arguing about?
Let's just for some possibilities, okay?
Like like like like just speculate. Just
use your imagination.
Let's throw ideas out out here. Let's
just brainstorm together. Okay. You have
a counterfeit and you have a spy arguing
about who's worse. How would they do
that?
>> Yes.
>> Uh because each of them feel like uh the
other one shouldn't be at the same level
where they are. You know, there like
every every every one of them feel like
they're superior and or like they're
condemned least like uh lesser sin than
than the others.
Yeah. Yeah. So, they're different,
right? And they're trying to figure out
like why they're together and they're
kind of pissed that they're together.
Yes. Yes.
>> Um like the alchemist, they both changed
the nature of reality.
So, Master Adam, he basically changed he
like um he changed money basically,
right? Or like he made fake money. So,
he changed the nature of money.
>> Yes. and Son changed um I mean he
basically
yeah
made
made the Trojans believe that it's a
horse that is is a present right for the
Trojans even though it basically
destroyed Troy so he changed
>> also their nature of reality
>> yeah so the similarity is that both are
changing
the perception of reality ity, right?
Who are manipulating the perception of
reality?
They're not alchemists who are
manipulating reality itself, but they
are changing people's perception of
reality, right? One by creating
counterfeit coins
and take advantage of
uh people's
reliance on money and the other is
giving false testimony or lying
in order to create
um
a different reality. Okay. So once a
once a counterfeit another is basically
like one of these um fake news
reporters, right?
Uh, yes.
>> I wonder if
maybe the counterfeitter doesn't fit,
but an impersonator is a form of theft,
but it's a specific you're stealing
someone's identity and which would be
like God's creation. You're stealing
something from God because God created
you in your identity where if I stole
your wallet,
God didn't create that.
Okay. So, why are they all together,
right? These all the falsifiers. They're
they're all different. Yes.
>> They all pray on people's trust.
>> They all pray on people's trust. They
take advantage of people's trust. But
this is an entire circle, right?
Uh yes,
>> they're all manipulating a larger trust.
So money is it's not just trust between
individuals, it's trust by society,
right? Um what's the other one? The
Trojan horse. This is this is you know
you're you're ending an entire
civilization,
>> right?
>> Altering the course of history,
I think this could be a step
more than alchemy because instead of
changing objects,
um, you're impersonating Mera
impersonated as a different person to
sleep with her father,
>> right?
>> And
I guess it's something that's supposedly
created by God and is transformed into
something that you can't trust. M
>> so you're not just manipulating objects
and soulless things.
>> You are manipulating things that
supposedly have a soul.
>> Yes. Okay.
Right.
>> Or you know another word uh whereas uh
in the less the lesser sinners uh they
might uh be stealing things or
destroying people's trust.
uh this group of sinners they create a
false trust.
>> Yes.
>> Uh which could be
uh you know meta trust meta severy. So
which is a higher level of sory.
>> Yes.
Okay.
Yes.
[snorts]
For alchemy, we said that to an extent
it's futile because it's to do with your
will. But [snorts]
I'm not sure the exact history of all
these people, but did they actually
succeed in doing?
>> But how do they succeed? What allowed
them to succeed in a way that alchemists
could not succeed?
Alchemists want to change the nature.
They want to change the fabric of
nature, right? You can't do that. That's
not what we can do.
What word is crucial to Dante that we
have not used today and basically
yesterday
>> consciousness maybe
>> why consciousness is important
>> because
it's
>> what do we what do we do with
consciousness our
>> connection with God consciousness or
imagination
>> in imagination okay all So, one
possibility, okay, and I'm just throwing
this out there for us to discuss, okay,
is is that the what what these four
people have in common is
hijacking the imagination.
Does that make sense? Okay. So, remember
in paradise,
the imagination is what makes us unique.
It's what makes us co-creators with God,
right? It's what allows the universe to
expand outwards.
But you could also use your imagination
for evil, right? And when you use it for
evil, what happens is the universe
contracts.
You're limiting people's imaginative
space. Does it make sense? You're
hijacking the imagination for evil ends
that brings evil to the world, right?
And before we always thought that
imagination is a good thing. Well, it
should be a good thing. It should be a
play and you can use it to create poetry
to create society. But there are people
who can hijack people's imaginations to
create evil in this world. Right? Does
that make sense? So, as a
counterfeitter, what you're doing is
you're hijacking people's imagination
that this money is very valuable. Right?
As a spy, you're hijacking hijacking
people's imagination that people tell
the truth.
The impostor hijacks people's
imagination
that only we can write our own wills,
right? So,
they're all hijacking imagination in
some way,
right? And if you think about it, for
Dante, this would be a lot worse than
trying to hijack nature.
Okay.
And this is interesting because
in our society then who are like the
worst people
to me?
No, not really. That that would be like
loss against uh acting against God in
nature, right? It'd be like sodomy and
uh incest. It it'd be in a circle of
violence. But this circle fraud. Uh,
yes.
>> Influencers on social media.
>> I think so. I think so. I I think that's
what Donn is saying here. Okay. And I
could be wrong, but it sounds like
social media influencers, people with
like huge followings, but not me, of
course. Um, they're the worst people
because they're hijacking the social
consciousness. They're hijacking the
social imagination.
Okay, I'm not any names because I I'll
get in trouble. But yes, you can you can
imagine certain people, right? Okay, so
that's what he's saying here.
Any Yes.
Yeah. Because I have heard in America
the highest the hierarchical uh crime is
not is not killer. It's just the people
who manipulate others and try to let
them believe that the lie is truth.
Look, look, I mean like this is hard for
people in China to appreciate, but media
people are really powerful in America.
You know, it's actually true in China.
Media people in China have absolutely no
power. But in America, if you work in
the media, you're really really
powerful. Okay.
>> Yesterday, one of the um participants
mentioned that in Heidi, the biggest
crime is fraud. So I mean a lot of fraud
happens when some voice AI voice
impersonates a father or mother or son
or daughter to get money from someone.
>> Right. Exactly. Right. Um
right. So so so you are with your social
media influence you could hijack the
imag imagination of millions of people.
So yeah [clears throat] I I think that's
what he's saying here. I could be wrong.
Okay. But I'm trying to figure out what
these poor people have in common because
they're so different on the surface,
right?
Okay. All right. Uh let's continue.
Count to 31.
The very tongue that first had wounded
me, sending the color up in both my
cheeks, was then to cure me with its
medicine, as did Achilles and his
father's lands, even as I have heard
when it dispensed a sad stroke first and
then a healing one. We turned our backs
upon that dismal valley by climbing up
the bank that girdles it. We made our
way across without a word. Here it was
less than night and less than day, so
that my sight could only move ahead
slightly. But then I heard a bugle blast
so strong it would have made a
thunderclap seem faint. At this my eyes
which doubled back upon their path
turned fully toward one place. Not even
Roland's born which followed on the s
the sad defeat when Charlemagne had lost
his holy army was as dread as this.
I'd only turned my head there briefly
when I seemed to make out many high
towers. And I asked him, "Master, tell
me what's the city?" and heed to me, it
is because you tried to penetrate from
far into these shadows that you have
formed such faulty images. When you have
reached that place, you shall see
clearly how much the distance has
deceived your sense, and therefore let
this spur you on your way." Then
lovingly he took me by the hand and
said, "Before we have moved farther on,
so that the fact may seem less strange
to you, I'd have you know they're not
towers, but giants, and from the navl
downward all of them are in the central
pit at the embankment. Just as whenever
mists begin to thin, when gradually
vision finds the form that in the vapor
thickened air was hidden, so I pierced
through the dense and darkened fog. As I
drew near, always nearer to the shore,
my error fled from me, my terror grew.
For as on its ground wall, Monty
Rajoni is crowned with towers. So
they're towered here above the bank that
runs around the pit with half that half
their bulk the terrifying giants whom Jo
still menaces from heaven when he sense
his bolts of thunder down upon them. and
I could now make out the face of one.
His shoulders and his chest, much of his
belly, and both his arms that hung along
his sides. Surely when she gave up the
art of making such creatures, nature
acted well indeed, depriving Mars of
instruments like these. And if she still
produces elephants and whales, whoever
sees with subtlety holds her, for this
to be more just and prudent, and where
the mind's acutest reasoning is joined
to evil will and evil power, there human
beings can't defend themselves. His face
appeared to me as broad and long as Rome
can claim, for it's St. Peter's pine
cone, his other bones shared in that
same proportion.
So that the bank which served him as an
apron down from his middle showed so
much of him above that three
Freezelanders would in vain have boasted
of their reaching to his hair. For
downward from the place where one would
buckle a mantle, I saw 30 spans of his.
Rafael Maya Zabi al-Mme began to bellow
that brute mouth for which no sweeter
psalms would be appropriate. and my
guide turned to him. Oh stupid soul,
keep to your horn and use that as an
outlet when rage or other passion
touches you. Look at your neck and you
will find the strap that holds it fast
and see bewildered spirit how it lies
straight across your massive chest. And
then to me he's his own accuser for this
is Nimrod through whose wicked thought
one single language cannot serve the
world. Leave him alone. Let's not waste
time and talk. For every language is to
him the same as his to others. No one
knows his tongue.
>> So Nimrod of course is the man who built
the Tower of Babel, right? And for his
crime
um
he now
whatever he says is gibberish. Okay,
he's incomprehensible. Okay, keep on
going. So turning to the left, we
journeyed on, and at the distance of a
bow, shot, found another giant, far more
huge and fierce, who was the master who
had tied him so. I cannot say, but his
left arm was bent behind him, and his
right was bent in front, both pinioned
by a chain that held him tight down from
the neck, and round the part of him that
was exposed. It has been wound five
times. This giant, in his arrogance, had
tested his force against the force of
highest Joe, my guide said. So he merits
this reward. His name is Ifaltis, and he
showed tremendous power in the giants
frightened the gods. The arms he moved
now moved no more. And I to him, if it
is possible, I'd like my eyes to have
experience of the enormous one, Briaras.
At which he answered, "You shall see
Antiaz nearby. He's unfettered and can
speak. He'll take us to the bottom of
all evil. The one you wish to see lies
far beyond and is bound up and just as
huge as this one and even more ferocious
in his gaze. No earthquake ever was so
violent when called to shake a tower so
robust as a falt quick to shake himself.
Then I was more afraid of death than
ever that fear would have been quite
enough to kill me had I not seen how he
was held by chains. And we continued on
until we reached Antius, who not
reckoning his head, stood out out above
the rock wall full of five L's.
Oh you who lived within the famous
valley where Shipio became the heir of
glory where Hannibal retreated with his
men, who took a thousand lions as your
prey, and had you been together with
your brothers in their high war, it
seems some still believe the sons of
earth would have become the victors. Do
set us down below where cold shuts and
cosetus
and do not disdain that task. Do not
send Don't send us onto Titus Tidius or
Typhen. This man can give you what is
long for here. Therefore, bend down and
do not curl your lip.
He still can bring you fame within the
world. For he's alive and still expects
long life, unless grace summon him
before his time. So said my master, and
in haste Antheus stretched out his hand,
whose massive grip had once been felt by
Hercules, Hercules, and grasped my
guide. And Virgil, when he felt himself
caught up, called out to me, "Come here
so I can hold you," then made one bundle
of himself and me. Just as the garisa
seems when seen beneath the leaning
side, when clouds run past and it hangs
down as if about to crash, so did Andyas
seemed to me as I watched him bend over
me. A moment when I'd have preferred to
take some other road. But gently on the
deep that swallows up both Lucifer and
Judas, he placed us, nor did he, so bent
over stay there long, but like a mast
above a ship, he rose. Okay. So now we
are now entering the final circle of
hell. Uh one comment is that Dante
creates symmetry, right? So remember in
paradise what lead what um what what
leads us to the imperium are are these
angels, right? And now as we enter the
final circle, um it's these giants that
lead us the way.
Um
I just put this out there, okay?
Why giants
in hell? Why angels in heaven? It's
obvious for angels in heaven, but why
giants in hell?
[snorts]
And again, you just have to use your
imagination because there's no answer.
Okay? You're going to like literally
look at footnotes and they won't ever
tell you why that why they're using
giants instead of instead of like I
don't know other things. Okay? You the
Dante, he demands your imagination. Yes.
>> It's kind of like how ants are afraid of
humans. We're afraid of things that are
giant in size and much bigger than us.
>> Okay.
[snorts] Yes.
It's also just ironic because giants we
usually associate with greatness and
good things, but this time they're
taking us to a bad place.
>> Okay. What are giants made of?
>> Clay, rocks, right? What is hell made
of?
Probably clay and rocks, right? What are
angels made of? Divine light, right?
What is heaven made of? Divine light.
So, so I I think that's that's what
what's happening here. Okay. These
giants are a literal expression of the
landscape of hell and the angels are a
literal literal expression of the
landscape of heaven. Okay. They're
manifestation of the um elements that
make heaven and hell possible. That's my
guess.
I also think that um with uh let's say
goodness and sin or perverseness of
goodness um there's something that's
insatiable about falling into the abyss.
>> Um and it's almost like um a snowball
that snowballs down that I think um it
just gets heavier heavier and keeps you
down.
>> Yes. That's really interesting. Exactly.
Right. So yeah, the the angels are
light. The he the giants are obviously
heavy, right? And that maybe that's a
metaphor for sin where the sin if you
commit one sin, you you keep on doing
another until it becomes a giant, right?
This the sin becomes a giant. Yes.
>> And I al also noticed that the giants
are basically silent. So they don't
speak they don't they don't speak much.
And I remember that the angels, they're
often um described as like they sing a
lot.
>> Yes.
>> And so I think like both
both angels and giants, they don't
really like speak human languages, but
like in heaven
um the soul is elevated into
um an expression of harmony and music.
>> Yes. Whereas in hell it's basically like
um
like
numbness and like silence.
>> That's beautiful. Yeah, that's brill
actually. This is something I would have
never come up with. Okay. So both Carol
and and you would like this is great.
Yes. Okay. And that's what Divine Comedy
is asking us to do to constantly use our
imagination. Okay. Don himself actually
doesn't know what he's trying to do.
Okay. He's just trying to excite our
imagination. Yes. And also another point
is that the angels if they're singing
it's like high vibration, high pitch,
right? The and if the giants aren't
speaking, it's low vibration, right?
>> You think about the etmology of discord
is literally discord
>> and a chord is harmony which is the
opposite of what you just mentioned with
heavenly music.
>> Wow. Okay. Okay. This is like really
interesting now. Okay. Yes. Any other
thoughts or comments?
Okay. So, so again, that's why the
Inferno, the Divine Comedy, it's it's
really the world's best literature
because it's constantly forcing us to
imagine new possibilities. Okay. All
right. So, um let's keep on going to uh
32.
[snorts]
Conto 32.
Had I the crude and scramal rhymes to
suit the melon melancholy hole upon
which all the other circling crags
converge and rest the juice of my
conception would be pressed more fully
but because I feel their lack I bring
myself to speak yet speak in fear.
>> Okay. Right. So that's why this music
idea is so important. Right? Because in
heaven it's this pure singing. Here it's
there's music but it's like sighing and
melancholing and groaning and despair
and apathy. Okay. So you can hear the
music but it's one of hell. Okay. Keep
on going.
For it is not a task to take in just to
show the base of all the universe. Not
for a tongue that cries out mama papa.
But may those ladies now sustain my
verse who helped Empon when he walled up
thieves so that my tale not differ from
the fact. Oh rabble miscreated past all
others there in the place of which it's
hard to speak. Better if here you had
not been goats or sheep. When we were
down below in the dark well beneath the
giant's feet and lower yet with my eyes
still upon the steep embankment. I heard
this said to me, "Watch how you pass.
Walk so that you not trample with your
souls the heads of your exhausted
wretched brothers. At this I turned and
saw in front of me beneath my feet a
lake that frozen fast had lost the look
of water and seam of glass.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. So this is why
Dante is such a genius. We are at the
very heart of hell. And when we think of
hell you think of like fire and
brimstone, right? and instead at the
very heart of hell is a frozen lake.
Okay. And so,
uh, he's just shocking. He's
revolutionary. Um, so this is something
that that we we'll think a lot more
about tomorrow. Okay. When I end Inferno
and discuss why is it that a center of
hell, it's a frozen lake rather than
like this raging fire as we would
expect. Um, we will also meet Lucifer.
Um, and you would think that Lucifer is
a king of hell, but we actually meet
Lucifer. He's not really the king of
hell. Okay. So, um, lots of
contradictions, lots of paradoxes,
and we will start to uh unra unravel
them tomorrow. Okay. So, we'll finish
Inferno tomorrow morning and we'll start
purgatory
um tomorrow afternoon. So, please um
review what we've learned. Please go
ahead and and read finish Inferno and
read the first five contos of Purgatory.
Uh I want to thank everyone for the
great discussion today. I actually
learned a lot from everyone today. A lot
of your comments just blew my mind.
Okay. I I I'm going to go home and think
a lot more about some of your comments
and some of your some of your um ideas.
So, but but that's the ideal seminar,
right? Where we're all learning from
each other, where where where we're all
contributing our own individuality to
the larger discussion. So, thank you so
much and great job today. Okay, I'll see
everyone tomorrow.